<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Choice experiences of the kind dealings of God before, in, and after conversion laid down in six general heads : together with some brief observations upon the same : whereunto is added a description of true experience / by J. Turner.</title>
            <author>Turner, J. (Jane)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 121 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09959798</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09959798</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1370:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Choice experiences of the kind dealings of God before, in, and after conversion laid down in six general heads : together with some brief observations upon the same : whereunto is added a description of true experience / by J. Turner.</title>
                  <author>Turner, J. (Jane)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 208+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hils,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: all after p. 208 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:1"/>
            <p>CHOICE EXPERIENCES OF The kind dealings of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in, and after CONVERSION; <hi>Laid down in ſix general Heads. Together with Some brief Obſervations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of true E X P E R I E N C E.</p>
            <p>By J. TURNER wife to Cap. <hi>John Turner.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALM 66. 16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come and hear all ye that fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. Hils,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Black ſpread-Eagle,</hi> and the <hi>Three Bibles</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:2"/>
            <head>To the Churches of Chriſt who worſhip God in ſpirit and truth according to the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of Jeſus Chriſt, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially thoſe my dear Brethren at <hi>Newcaſtle, Barwick,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> with whom I have taken ſweet counſel in the houſe of God for ſeveral years paſt, grace, mercy, truth and peace be multiplied from the Lord Jeſus Christ.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>RECIOUS and dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Brethren, I know it would ſeem
<pb facs="tcp:44402:3"/> very ſtrange to you, if this following Treatiſe ſhould come to your hands without my pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick owning of it, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed well it might, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering my neer relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Author; it is no ſmall joy to my heart that the Lord is pleaſed in theſe our daies any way by any means to put his People in mind of that which they are ſo prone to
<pb facs="tcp:44402:3"/> forget, namely the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious workings of God in their poor hearts, which you will find in this ſmall Treatiſe in theſe three generall heads, <hi>viz.</hi> before, in, and ſince Converſion; we find the Lord in Scripture often calling upon his People to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted ſtate, <hi>Iſaiah 51. 1. Look unto the Rock whence ye are hewen, and
<pb facs="tcp:44402:4"/> to the holy of the Pit whence ye are digged;</hi> And the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our great inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to forget it, he is pleaſed to mind us of it, as in <hi>Eph. 5. 8. 1 Cor. 6. 10, 11. Tit. 3. 3. Eph. 2. 1, 2, 3. &amp;c.</hi> The right remembrance of our unconverted ſtate will be a means to engage our hearts to be much in the thoughts of, and highly to priſe, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable
<pb facs="tcp:44402:4"/> love and grace of our God through Ieſus in quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, in tranſlating us from the Kingdome of darkneſs into the Kingdome of his dear Son; the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pondering of theſe things in our hearts will ſweetly force us to break forth into admiration with the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Ioh. 3. 1, 2. Behold what
<pb facs="tcp:44402:5"/> manner of love the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be call'd the ſons of God, &amp;c.</hi> but when we forget the two former, we loſe our communion with God in a great meaſure, and cannot priſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the kind dealings of our God with us, ſince <hi>Converſion,</hi> neither walk holily and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently before the Lord in all his holy appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:44402:5"/> as we ought, but leave an open door for Satan to deceive us with his manifold ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, by which we ſuffer much harm.</p>
            <p>My hearts deſire and prayer to the Lord is, that he would give all his people more care and diligence in watching their own hearts and waies, for the increaſe of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſtrength and
<pb facs="tcp:44402:6"/> growth in grace, leſt they being led away for a time, with the error of the wicked, fall from their own ſtedfaſtneſs, <hi>2 Pet. 3. 17, 18.</hi> as many have done to their greateſt grief and loſs. Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Brethren, you have here the labours of one of the weakeſt ſex, which I truſt will occaſion you the more to give glory to God, in that his
<pb facs="tcp:44402:6"/> ſtrength appears in weakneſs; were it not for the relation, I ſhould have much room to ſpeak of the Author, and this Her work, but I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, Let Her works praiſe Her; only I have this that I cannot but ſay, it was not Her deſire to publiſh it, Her reaſons She hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Secondly, So far as one can ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:44402:7"/> for another, I can ſay for my Wife, in this vvork ſhe hath had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle help from men or things, but I believe much from the Lord; and as the Lord hath ovvned and much aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted her in theſe her great labors, I truſt the ſame povver vvill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company each precious heart, into vvhoſe hand it may come, to make it very profitable to
<pb facs="tcp:44402:7"/> them. At my firſt ſight of it, which was when it was neer fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, though I believe I was the firſt that ſaw it, next Her ſelf, I was ſo ſurprized, knowing nothing of it before, that I knew not what to ſay of it; but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſideration, and reviewing of it, I was very much preſſed in ſpirit to publiſh it, and the more, in that the
<pb facs="tcp:44402:8"/> oftner I read it, the more I was ingaged to it: I can ſay through mercy it hath been uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and profitable to me; I hope it will be ſo to many more. It is no ſmall mercy, nor low attainment, to be indeed an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Chriſtian; it is eaſier to have fine words than a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the heart: but ſeeing the kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:44402:8"/> is all glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and that our treaſure there doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by the bleſſing of the Lord upon our diligent uſing that means ordained for that end; this I truſt will be a faithfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer and helper of us in this great work, in which I hope the Lord will have much glory, and his people comfort, which hath
<pb facs="tcp:44402:9"/> been, is, and I truſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be, the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poor unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Brother in the Goſpel, JOHN TURNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:9"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou wilt find in this little Book ſomething ſuitable to thoſe various changes, and differing conditions that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily poor ſouls are in, both before, in, and after converſion (only excepting a high degree of viſible profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and exceſs of riot, with heart, hand and tongue blaſpheming the holy One of Iſrael, in an unconverted State) The Author was kept from that great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of wickedneſs, as you will find in the beginning of Her book. If this ſhall come into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of any that yet live in thoſe pollutions, and abominable corruptions, the Lord teach them to conſider, that if Civility and Morality be too low and too little to ſtand the Soul in any ſtead in that day when God will judge the ſecrets of all men by Jeſus Christ; Surely then ſin and profaneſs will be a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable covering. This little Treatiſe is not intended principally for ſuch <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maelites,</hi> but rather for thoſe who have
<pb facs="tcp:44402:10"/> their faces <hi>Zion</hi> ward enquiring the way thither, as alſo to ſuch as have a name and place where the honor of God dwells, to all ſuch I may ſay as an incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to peruſe this little Treatiſe, Firſt, as to the nature of it, its that which hath been digested, and it may well be called Experience, it may be likned to the Wine that Christ made of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the end of the Mariage-Feast, being last it was better than the firſt, though doubtles the first wine was good: So I hope thou wilt find theſe few lines, though good at the firſt, yet better at the latter end, it being the privilege of Saints to have their laſt works best, and as they grow in years to grow in grace; which the Lord grant unto all his, for his mercies ſake.<hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN TURNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:10"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot but take it as a mercy from the Lord, that I have ſuch an opportunity to give my te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony unto ſo worthy a work as this is, which indeed is a work that is not common amongſt men, being the work of a Daughter of <hi>Zion,</hi> nay I may ſay a Mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as it is ſaid, <hi>Many Daughters have done vertuouſly, but She excelleth them all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let Her own works praiſe Her in the Gates of Zion,</hi> who hath opened to the view
<pb facs="tcp:44402:11"/> of all, not only the counſel of mans heart, which is as the deep waters, with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits therof, in which it may miſcarry through the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the fleſh, and the wiles of Satan, but alſo the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful wiſdom of God, in the powerful operation of his Spirit, in the clear footſteps of his Grace, by a large and well grounded experience in the Lords bringing of a poor ſoul out of darkneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to light, but in more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thus; How far a ſoul may be wrought upon before it comes to Chriſt, with the lets and hinderances that
<pb facs="tcp:44402:11"/> keep it off from the truth. Secondly, of the true work of Grace in the heart, and how this differs from the former. Thirdly, the ſouls cloſing with Chriſt, and the ſweet enjoyments of the ſame. And laſtly, the full e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment in the free Grace of God, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how God effected this, with the ſeveral effects of all the aforeſaid degrees of Grace, with ſo much vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of ſpiritual, ſoul-edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter, and all ſo full of life and delight to a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious experienced heart, that as to my remembrance I have
<pb facs="tcp:44402:12"/> not heard of the like, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a large diſcovery of the moſt deviliſh and ſtrong deluſions of our times and the depth and danger of them, with the great Soul-loſſes of ſuch as are taken with them, and alſo the nature and tendency of them, and Gods rich mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in his recovering of his own out of them, and how by his wiſdome he makes the ſame work for their good. So that good Reader, if thou wouldſt ſee the very inſide of a gracious ſoul, with the largeſt experience of the riches of Gods great diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations
<pb facs="tcp:44402:12"/> of grace, here it is clearly preſented in this ſmal enſuing Treatiſe, being ſo ſeaſonable for the time we live in, and ſo uſeful for all ſorts of perſons, wherein error and hereticks are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, the godly moſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly edified, and the way of truth laid open for ſuch as deſire it, and many precious principles of truth ſoundly aſſerted; All which, with much more conſidered, did not only affect my ſoul, but cauſed me, with others, to preſs on the author hereof to publiſh the ſame for the good of Saints, and a glorious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb facs="tcp:44402:13"/> for all Chriſtians to follow, in a ſerious obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the paſſages of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and grace, that they may be rich in experience of his free mercies and goodnes towards them, as that by which God holds our ſouls in life, and forms his image in us, with deep ingagements of love and zeal for his glory, into whoſe boſome I commit the godly Reader, and this good work unto his bleſſing upon thy heart, and remain the unworthieſt of all Saints,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Spilsbery.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:13"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis ſmal Volume is the fruit of private Meditations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the inward man, which many neglecting have been like painted Sepulchers. It is a known Maxim, That the ſerious minded Chriſtian is the moſt thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, especially when the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ordereth the affection. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons are ſo drowned in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and immethodical thoughts, that all their intentions are like an untimely birth, or the graſs on the houſe top. This Author hath obtained favour of the Lord not
<pb facs="tcp:44402:14"/> onely to be eſteemed a Daughter of Sion, but alſo one that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in grace, and to be counted a Mother in the true Iſrael, of which we have not many. I speak not this by hearſay onely (though her works praiſe her in the gates) but having had for ſome years more than ordinary experience of her clear conceptions, and ſound judgement; being more naturally given to the exerciſe of godlineſs with ſobriety than others, hath ſtirred me up to teſtify ſome of her spiritual worth, which hath been very advantagious to many, but especially to me. It was the great ſorrow of the Jewiſh woman to be barren, being thereby deprived
<pb facs="tcp:44402:14"/> of bringing forth Chriſt in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature; and it is greater ſorrow to ingenious Chriſtians to be barren in spirituals. This precious ſoul hath conceived and brought forth spiritual fruit, to the view of good and bad; the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter containeth a gradual narration of the Lords various dealings with her many years, both in, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Converſion, which speaketh forth much obſervance of Gods daily footſteps in the ſoul, the like have not commonly been ſeen; few have given-themſelves to be intent in diſcovering the beauty of Chriſt in the inward man. If this may be inſtrumental to bring forth the additional experiences
<pb facs="tcp:44402:15"/> of other Saints, it will be a good preſident, especially in this age, in which Saints time hath been occaſionally taken up more in building the walls of the true Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than in diſcovering the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Grace and inward Glory of Chriſt in the ſoul.</p>
            <p>Theſe inward Experiences are not intended to limit others, but to provoke ſelf-examination and spiritual quickning. They are orderly laid down, though with brevity; a word to the wiſe is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Here is the danger of ſin diſcovered, the excellent ſafety of a ſoul in Chriſt declared, the duties of privileged Chriſtians manifeſted, and ſome cautions
<pb facs="tcp:44402:15"/> laid down to take heed of a light and unſound Generation of men, whoſe deceits have been largely experienced. Be watchfull, leſt you fall where others have ſtumbled, and are through Grace recovered and much eſtabliſhed. Read with diligence, conſider with patience; thy encouragements are many; that which is tendred being the fruit of the Spirit of grace doth invite and animate thee; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, thy labor ſhall not be in vain in the Lord, to whom I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thee in this and all thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual labours, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated at <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Moneth 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy affectionat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and welwiſhing friend JOHN GARDNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44402:16"/>
            <head>A word from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the READER.</head>
            <p>THeſe notes in the following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe are ſome of the fruits of my labours written at ſeveral times in my Husbands abſence, which may be ſome ſatisfaction as to my ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that time. I did intend them only for my own private uſe, as a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer of the old loving kindneſs of the Lord towards me, &amp; twas not in the leaſt in my thoughts that ever it ſhould have been preſented to a publick view, but after I had written the greatest part of it, ſhewing it to my Husband, he had ſome thoughts to publiſh it, judging it might be profitable to ſome precious ſouls which, though it be written but in a broken, ſcattering way, and I am conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to my ſelf of too much weakneſs and unworthineſs to be an Inſtrument for the
<pb facs="tcp:44402:16"/> good of ſouls, or to propagate the leaſt truth of the Lord Jeſus, yet I ſhall be willing to ſubmit to better Judgements, hoping through the Bleſſing of God it may be uſeful, knowing from my own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I have received much from the Lord by reading: but beſides the ſenſe of my own unworthineſs, as I had ſome diſcouraging thoughts as to my writing of it at the firſt, ſo I have met with the like as to my giving way to the publiſhing of it. As firſt, I thought I might ſeem to ſome to walk in an untrodden path, I having never ſeen any thing written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this manner and method; but whatever entertainment it may find with ſuch, knowing from whom I have received it, I am well ſatisfied, my foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps will be found as for matter, ſo for method and manner, among the foot-ſteps of the flock of Chriſt, where I deſire to feed beſides the Shepheards Tents, <hi>Cant. 1. 8,</hi> Another thought which did diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me was, knowing I must expect to encounter with Satan in relation to it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral waies, but believing that which way ſoever he appears whether to abaſe or exalt me in my own thoughts, the
<pb facs="tcp:44402:17"/> Lord will not be wanting with ſtrength to withstand and reſist him, and that I ſhall with advantage be delivered from his ſnares and temptations: Thus reſolving to commit my ſelf and it to the bleſſing of the Almighty, deſiring it may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Saints as the widows mite, and that what is weak may be covered with love, is the deſire of me the unworthy Servant of Chriſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IANE TURNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44402:17"/>
            <head>The manner how I was put upon the writing theſe following lines, with the reaſons and grounds for doing the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrough the good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, I li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Newcastle</hi> for ſome time, where I received many precious mercies from the Lord, which I deſire may never be forgotten by me; and being under a bodily afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Lord was pleaſed ſo to viſit me with his loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that I can truly ſay, it was a time of joy to my ſoul: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44402:18"/> I never enjoyed ſo much ſweet communion with God, for ſo long a time together, as I did at that time; for, for the ſpace of ſeven or eight weeks together, I was in a continual converſe and exchanging love with God, as it were lodging and living in the boſome of Chriſt; and truly I do not remember that in all that time I had one conſiderable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption; which condition was ſo ſweet and joious to me, that it did exceedingly grieve me to think that ever I ſhould forget the particulars thereof, finding from ſad experience, that (though I can never forget the ſubſtance of ſuch things, yet) I am prone to forget the particulars, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of which I find to be much for the glory of God, and my own comfort and profit, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in times of trial and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44402:18"/> upon the conſideration of which I thought it might be a good way to write them down.</p>
            <p>And calling to mind ſome of the old loving kindneſſes of God towards me, I reſolved to write down ſome of them: For I do believe I cannot remember the hundreth part of the kind deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God towards me, ſo as to write them all: but though I cannot remember all; yet I may remember ſome, and thoſe I judg moſt conſiderable I reſolved to write them down.</p>
            <p>But as I had many thoughts of encouragement to do it, ſo I had ſome thoughts that did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me; As</p>
            <p>Firſt, I thought it would be very hard, if not impoſſible, for me to remember that which hath been ſo long ſince (ſo as to write it) But the Lord was pleaſed to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44402:19"/> ſatisfy me in this; that my ends being ſuch as were agreeable to his will, he would according to his promiſe, in my endeavours, bring things to my remembrance: and truly I was confirmed in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving he would ſo do, from my own experience, for I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ever I ſet my ſelf ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to meditate on the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer kindneſs of God towards me, but I was much refreſhed by it, and remembred that which I ſeemed to have forgotten.</p>
            <p>A Second thought which did diſcourage me was, fearing left through forgetfulneſs as I knew I ſhould leave out ſomething which was, ſo I might poſſibly write ſomething which was not, which I would not by any means willingly do; this I diſcerned to be a temptation for fear of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, but God was pleaſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44402:19"/> to ſatisfy me in it, with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that what I did I would do as in his preſence, and that if there were any thing which was clear to my remembrance, that I could not bring in without ſomething which was doubtfull, I would rather leave out the one, than write the other, much leſs write any thing which was a plain addition, and in this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution I ſet upon it, believing that God would aſſiſt and help me, deſiring not to give way to diſcouraging thoughts; for I have often experienced this, that if in writing, ſpeaking, or doing of any thing whereby God may be glorified, we ſhould give way to temptations and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we ſhould do nothing at all: For Satan and our own hearts will not be wanting to us, that way.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44402:20"/> But with grief of heart I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that the greateſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that I have met with have been from the Saints themſelves (I do not mean only as to this particular, but as to other ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al duties alſo) by which I truſt I have learned in ſome meaſure to take the more heed how I diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others; and doubtleſs Saints ought to take great heed left by their giving juſt occaſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement they quench the Spirit of God in them, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>quench not the Spirit;</hi> which that we may not do, we ought to endeavour for a Spirit of diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and for ſuch a carriage by which we may beſt draw forth the hearts of others in ſpiritual things; not that we ſhould draw or put perſons upon that which they have not received, or that we ſhould encourage any who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44402:20"/> put themſelves on ſuch things, but rather reprove them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe who ſo act in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique way, ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, who would be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Law, when indeed they know not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 7. the hearing of which hath been no ſmall burthen to my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. I wiſh from my ſoul, that not onely particular Saints may be faithful in the diſcharge of their duty, to reprove ſuch, but alſo that the Church would put forth their Authority for the calling of them in, and that ſuch bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren onely whoſe gifts are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by the Church, may exerciſe their gifts publiquely, and no other, that the Saints may not be burthened, nor the world blaſpheme. I ſhall ſay no more as to this, believing that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44402:21"/> the Lord will inſtruct thoſe that are called to that work, namely to judge who are fit to be teachers, deſiring only to caution Saints to take heed of caſting ſtumbling blocks in each others way: For doubtleſs, though its one of the laſt, yet its not the leaſt trial, that after we have in a great meaſure overcome the world, the devil, and our own hearts, we ſhould meet with lets and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from one another.</p>
            <p>Its that indeed which is ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to an imperfect ſtate in which we are, and by which we may learn, as to live more ſingly on God, ſo alſo to preſſe after, and long for, that perfect State in which we ſhall be at the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. I might enlarge much in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but I intend only to hint at things, deſiring the Lord to ſtir
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44402:21"/> up the hearts of ſome more able, to enlarge upon it, knowing there is great need that Saints ſhould be exhorted to this duty, namely not to diſcourage but to, incourage one another in all good things; &amp; I deſire that we may ſet before us that exhortation of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal. 5. 26: Let us not be deſirous of vain glory, provoking one another, envying one another;</hi> From whence I obſerve, that to be deſirous of vain glory, makes way for a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of envy, and ſo to provoke and grieve one another.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture with <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 5. may through the bleſſing of God be very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Saints for this purpoſe: for queſtionles a ſlighting of the gifts and grace of God in others, doth many times ariſe off a deſire of vain glory, and a ſpirit of envy.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:44402:22"/>
               <head>The firſt Note of Experience of the good Providence of God towards mee in a ſtate of Ignorance and Darkneſs before Converſion.</head>
               <p>IT pleaſed the Lord I was civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought up from a child, and kept from ſuch groſs evills as perſons meerly civil do not allow, but otherwaies very vain; and that which inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally kept me from ſuch things, as I conceived, was (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my civil educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) a deſire of happineſs, and a fear of miſery, having a general notion that ſinne was attended with miſery; for I remember, when I had done any thing that I thought was ſin, I was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44402:22"/> preſently under great fear and terror; to take off which, and alſo to attain happineſs in the end, I thought I was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in ſome kind of religion, but being very ignorant, I made no inquiry what religion was, but took it for granted that that was religion which was then in force from King and Biſhops, and ſo going on I grew very ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly zealous in all things ſuitable to the ſervice Book, or a Cathedrall kind of Worſhip, and I thought the more I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in faſting, book pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and obſervation of daies and times, mourning and afflicting my ſelf for ſin, the better it was; ſo that I think I did exceed moſt that I knew in that way for blind zeal, and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous devotion: yet at this very time I thought my ſelf far from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44402:23"/> Popery, and did alwaies oppoſe that with much zeal, and I am ſure with much ignorance.</p>
               <p>Then being acquainted with ſome who were then called Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, I began to perceive that there was ſome difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt that which I practiſed, and that which was done by them; and my obſervation of their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and hearing them ſpeak ſuch language as I was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſtranger to, did ſo far work upon me, that I began to queſtion my own condition, and oft times when I had done my long book prayers, though I had ſcarce ever heard of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without a book, yet I would in a poor broken manner com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to God that I was in ſome fear that what I did was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, and if it were not, I did beg of him that he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44402:23"/> would bring me to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth whatever I did undergo for attaining of it: But then ſometimes I thought my condition good enough, and though I was never given to rail or ſpeak evil of ſuch perſons, yet I thought they made more ado than they need to have done, and that God did not require ſo much ſtrictneſſe as they ſeemed to plead for.</p>
               <p>But hearing them ſpeak much of knowledge, and of the danger of ignorance, and knowing my ſelf to be very ignorant, I began to be more frequent in reading the Scriptures, and hearing ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; but my underſtanding not being yet opened, it was to little effect; for I remember I was at this time like a ſtock or ſtone as to the true underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that which I read or heard,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44402:24"/> that I can truly ſay as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in <hi>Pſal. 73. 22. So fooliſh was I and ignorant, even as a Beaſt before thee;</hi> and yet at this time I was ſomething in affection, as when I heard any thing of the judgements of God againſt ſin, I ſhould tremble, and when any thing of the mercy and goodneſs of God, or the love and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Jeſus Chriſt, my heart would melt (as I thought) yet I underſtood nothing, ſo as to have it ſeated in the underſtanding and judgement.</p>
               <p>This in general I do remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as to that ſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="observations">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:44402:24"/>
               <head>Some brief Obſervations from this note of Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, concerning my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept from ſin by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of happineſs, and fear of miſery: From thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That in the daies of ignorance, before we have received grace to restrain us from ſin, its a mercy to be restrained by ſomething elſe:</hi> And truly to me its a mercy ſo conſiderable, that I deſire to bleſs the Lord for it as long as I live.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:44402:25"/>
               <p>Secondly, concerning my ſeeking after and framing to my ſelf ſome kind of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That its naturall for perſons to make after ſome kind of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and rather than they will worſhip nothing, they will wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Samaritan like, they know not what,</hi> John 4. 22.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, concerning my oppoſing Popery, when my ſelf lived in the practice of the ſame thing for the nature of it, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a perſon may oppoſe an error, and yet live at that time in the ſame error for the nature of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44402:25"/> it, though in a lower degree, and not know it;</hi> And that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons totally ignorant, but Saints alſo, if they take not good heed: for I have experienced this more times than once.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, concerning my complaint and prayer to God in relation to truth, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a perſon before converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may (for ought I know) truly pray, and that from a ſecret work of God upon the heart.</hi> And therefore though I cannot from Scripture-rule exhort ſuch to pray, ſo neither from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44402:26"/> ence can I forbid them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reioyce to ſee the hearts of any run out in ſuch a way.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, concerning my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much affected with truth, though I underſtood it not, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ignorant perſons in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth may have their reaſon ſo far touched, that they may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it, and be much affected with it, and yet underſtand no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo as to have it ſeated in the heart and judgement;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not ſeated in the heart and iudgement, that I conceive is the reaſon why ignorant perſons are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and ſo unconſtant in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44402:26"/> their thoughts concerning truth, and why many that live a long time under much means, yet continue very ignorant, it may be <hi>ever lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2 Ti. 3. 7. and as the ſeed upon the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ground withred away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had no root; So truth not being rooted in the heart and iudgement, though it ſpring up in much affection, yet it comes to nothing. And indeed ignorant perſons many times are ſooner affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and doe ſeem to have more affection than others; he reaſon of that I conceive)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44402:27"/> is the ſame alſo with that of the ſeed upon the ſtony ground, it ſprang up ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, becauſe it had not depth of earth; ſo its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral for ignorant perſons to ſpring forth in affection, they having as it were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to do but onely to be affected; their ſtrength running all in one vein, or in one Chanel, they ſpend all in affection, while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have more under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding have many other things to do, all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their ſouls being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, their ſtrength is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44402:27"/> into many veins, weighing and pondering things in the heart and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it may have depth to root and ſettle there; as its ſaid of <hi>Mary, ſhee pondred thoſe things in her heart,</hi> Luke 2. 19. ſo they are trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring it up in their hearts, having in their <hi>treaſury things new and old.</hi> Mat. 12. 35. and 13. 52. and a little affection where there is iudgement, is better than a great deal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudgement; yet much affection with a ſound iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is beſt of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44402:28"/>
               <head>The ſecond note of Experience, How I was brought to ſee my ſelf in a miſerable ſtate by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and convinced of ſin by the Law, and ſo converted to du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, labouring for life by doing, though at that time in my own thoughts far from owning ſuch a thing.</head>
               <p>By providence hearing a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Nation who was then called a Puritan, whom though I uſed often to hear, yet I could truly ſay as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in <hi>Dan. 10. 8. I heard, but I understood not;</hi> and as I was once hearing of him, very ſuddenly I thought I did diſcern and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand things more clearly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44402:28"/> and more diſtinctly than ever I did before that time, being much affected with it, and did then own God in it, having many ſuch thoughts as theſe, that as it was ſaid of <hi>Lydia, Act.</hi> 16. 14. that now the Lord had opened my underſtanding, and now I hoped I ſhould have more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and delight more in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reading, whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was wearyſome to me, becauſe I did not underſtand any thing but in a confuſed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>After this I had a great delight to hear this man, and though I thought it much on any other occaſion to go one mile on foot, yet to hear him I could go three, and back again the ſame day fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently; and by his Miniſtery I was brought to ſee the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious varity of my former zeal,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44402:29"/> and laid it aſide; and I remember that at this time I had ſuch affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate heart-workings towards God and godlineſs, and ſuch a hatred of all ſin, according to what I then knew, that I did many times in my ſerious thoughts chuſe rather to dy than live, meerly upon that account, becauſe I would not ſin againſt God, knowing my ſelf ſubject thereunto.</p>
               <p>And though I cannot ſay that at this time I had faith in God, ſo as to believe his Love to me on Goſpel grounds, for I was total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant of any ſuch thing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years after, yet I had good thoughts of God from that glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering light which I then had, and which did produce in me much love to him, as I cannot but ſo judge.</p>
               <p>But no ſooner was I brought
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44402:29"/> to this, but Satan was ready to aſſault me, and ſet upon me with this horrid temptation, to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the Being of <hi>God,</hi> and I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it uſually came upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me when I was alone, but eſpecially as I was going by my ſelf to hear the aforeſaid Miniſter, inſomuch that it did exceedingly trouble me, and I then diſcerned it to be a temptation, and did reſiſt and labour againſt it, drawing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as I went in the fields from the very works of Creation, to confirm my ſelf in this truth, that there is a <hi>God,</hi> that it ſhould not be in vain for me or any to ſerve him; and earneſtly crying to God againſt it, through Grace I was not overcome by it, but had a ſupply of ſtrength until it was removed; and I was no more troubled with it in many years after.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44402:30"/>
               <p>So I continued a conſtant hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of this man, and other ſuch like, for ſome years, by which I came to ſee my ſelf in a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble State by nature, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of ſin by the Law; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very ignorant of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and their doctrine, being for the moſt part ſuch as was ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the old covenant, inſtead of going to Chriſt for life, I was brought to a great degree of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and travell for life and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, by doing (though at that time in my own thoughts farre from owning ſuch a thing) being as exact and ſtrict in all my waies (I think I may ſay) as it was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a poor creature to be, but the more ſtrict I was, ſtill look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the glaſſe of the law, the more my bondage was increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; For I could ſee nothing but an addition of ſin in all that I did,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44402:30"/> the law ſtill calling for a perfect righteouſneſs:</p>
               <p>Then I began to be very much troubled, and in a great amaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; perplexity of ſpirit, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I ſhould periſh for ever; then I had thoughts to diſcover my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to ſome to have adviſe from them, but meeting with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſcouragements, did not, but kept it in my own breſt, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering no more but what I could not hide, which was onely my outward appearance much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from what formerly it was, which did occaſion ſome to ſay that I was neer a diſtraction, they not knowing what condition I was in.</p>
               <p>And truly my condition was ſo ſad that I was afraid of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction my ſelf; for I thought it impoſſible to continue long in that condition, and not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44402:31"/> which fear did occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to apply my ſelf to ſome means of comfort, whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was not willing to hearken to any thing that way: the means I uſed was chiefly reading &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by which it pleaſed the Lord I came to ſome dark apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning Jeſus Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that nature, which if I could get a right underſtanding of, my condition would be much better; but fearing left I ſhould ſink under my burthen, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations comming on me like the waves of the Sea, I was forced as I went about my occaſions often to cry to God, like the Diſciples in another caſe, <hi>Lord ſave me, elſe I periſh, Mat.</hi> 8. 25. I thought many times, I was even ſinking under my burthen, and I did believe there was no help but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44402:31"/> only in the Lord, and that he was able to do it, but whether he would do it, or whether he would ſave or damn me at laſt, I knew not, neither did I think it poſſible for me ever to have known that, except it were by ſome extraordinary way, which very few did attain unto.</p>
               <p>But by degrees I began to ſtay upon ſome promiſes through ſuch conſiderations as theſe; firſt, I thought it could not ſtand with the goodneſs of God to damn a poor ſoul that had ſuch heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workings and deſires after him as I had, having much in my thoughts thoſe words of <hi>Sampſons</hi> Mother, <hi>Judges</hi> 13. 23. I thought that if he did intend to deſtroy me he would never have given me ſuch deſires after him, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved me till now; and then that promiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 6. did much ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44402:32"/> me, for I thought that if ever poor creature did hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs, I did; theſe promiſes and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, with ſome confuſed apprehenſions that I had concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lord Jeſus, did much raiſe me; the thoughts I had of him were ſuch as theſe, I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Juſtice of God muſt be ſatisfied for ſin, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ſatisfy his juſtice but a perfect righteouſneſſe, now I thought I was to be very ſtrict and circumſpect in all my waies, if it were poſſible, to perform ſuch a righteouſneſſe, but what I could not do, Chriſt had done for me, and when I had done any thing that I thought was ſin, I could not apply Chriſt till I had repented, that was till I had mourned, faſted and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, afflicting my ſelf in ſuch a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44402:32"/> meaſure as I thought might ſtand with the not deſtroying or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicing nature, for there God would have mercy rather than ſacrifice, and Jeſus Chriſt would make up that which was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: ſo that Chriſt was my ſtay, though it was through a very car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and wrong apprehenſion.</p>
               <p>But though I thought I muſt be ſo qualified and fitted for Chriſt before I could receive him, and be made happy by him, yet I knew there was no mercy to be found without him, nor no life but in him: In this conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I lived ſome years more, and grew very cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; confident (as I think it was poſſible to be, under ſuch an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion) but yet my confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was alwaies more or leſſe, as I was more or leſs ſtrict in my waies, and ſometimes though I had been never ſo ſtrict yet I was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44402:33"/> ſubject to fear left I had not done as much as it was poſſible for me to do, for otherwaies I thought Chriſt would be nothing at all to me; yet my hopes were greater than my fears, and I was reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if I periſhed, I would periſh here at the feet of Chriſt: and now I did not only ſee that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible which before I thought im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, but I had great hopes and much confidence moſt times.</p>
               <p>This apprehenſion, though it be that which is far below the glory of the free grace of God in the Goſpel, yet it did preſent Chriſt very lovely to me, and did produce in me a real love to him, as I dare not but ſo judge, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how I ſtood affected to, and delighted in, whatever I knew to be his will: Though I muſt confeſs I think at the firſt the great wheel that carryed all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44402:33"/> about, was my own good; yet I am very confident that at this time I had a real love to, &amp; delight in, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his commandements were not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to me, but I did approve of them to be the moſt excellent things, becauſe approved of by the Lord; and I well remember I was ſo far taken off from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in ſin, that I think I may ſay I did hate it with a perfect hatred, as that which was in it ſelf the only object of hatred, as it was againſt God, and all my delight was to be with thoſe that I thought did excell in vertue, and I could not bear wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but their waies and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were odious to me; yet ſtill I ſay my condition at this time was a condition of extreme bondage and below the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſay no more of it, but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44402:34"/> only this, that what I have here written I think I may ſay is not the hundredth part of the labors and travells of my ſoul whiles I lived in that condition, and if I ſhould go about to write it all, I know not how nor when to make an end. But God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in mercy to free me from that bondage by the manifeſtation of his love and grace through his Son, to whom be all praiſe and glory for ever more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observations">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:44402:34"/>
               <head>Some brief Obſervations from this ſecond note of Experience.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Concerning the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by whom my experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, which was one (as I iudge) not rightly called or ſent to preach the Goſpel, he not being related to a true Church, though otherwiſe (I hope) a godly man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that meaſure of light he had received.</p>
               <p>From whence I obſerve, <hi>That it is poſſible for a godly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44402:35"/> man in times of ignorance and darkneſs to be a Miniſter of a falſe Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I obſerve, <hi>That though it be not the work of a falſe Miniſtery, neither is it the way of God to convert ſouls by,</hi> yet accidentally or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntially ſomthing may be done that way by them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in times of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where there is not a true Miniſtry abroad; as indeed I am much inclined to own the work of converſion to be begun in me at this time, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe now was the day of Gods power no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44402:35"/> only to make me willing, but there was ſome change wrought in the whole ſoul; and every faculty of it, which before was dead, had now ſome life and motion in things relating to God and godlineſs; as the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding was opened, ſo the will was changed, and made willing to ſubmit to truth, and to imbrace the waies of life, though it were through the greateſt difficulty, yet in much darkneſs; and then the affections were taken, and though there were but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle glimps of truth appeared, yet there was a love to it,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44402:36"/> and delight in it, and a great hatred of the contrary; all which I apprehend could not be but from ſome ſeeds of the Goſpel, though through falſe teaching, there was not that bleſſed fruit of ioy and peace in believing; alſo the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory was active and buſie to retain truth, ſo that here was ſome change wrought in the whole ſoul as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>A ſecond reaſon is, becauſe when I lay under conviction of ſin by the Law, and was ready to ſink under my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that which did ſuport and uphold my ſpirit was the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, though
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44402:36"/> my apprehenſions of him were not according to the Goſpel, as to the glory of the free grace therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
               <p>A third reaſon is, from the conſideration of that fruit which did appear at that time, which was an intire love to Chriſt, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation ſuitable thereunto, according to the light then received: For there was not only a doing good, but a love to it, and delight in it; and there was not only a forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring evil, but a hatred and indignation againſt it. It being thus with me at this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44402:37"/> time, I cannot but much ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der perſons in the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who do manifeſt by a good converſation, a reall work of God upon their hearts, though living in a diſcovery below the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges of the Goſpel: yet not ſo to tender them, as not to tender the glory of truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them, being true to my principles in keeping a ſtrict ſeparation from them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to their viſible and publick worſhip, it being contrary to the rule of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Three Obſervations from the three foregoing reaſons.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44402:37"/> Firſt, concerning the Change wrought in the whole ſoul, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That there may be a Change wrought in the whole ſoul to life and godlineſs, long before that ſoul comes to enjoy life by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, concerning my being ſtaid upon Chriſt when I was like to ſink up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my burthen, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a ſoul may cleave to, and really ſtay upon Chriſt, through ſome apprehenſion which preſents him lovely, though it may be that which doth not preſent him ſo lovely as indeed he is.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:44402:38"/>
               <p>Thirdly, concerning that entire love I had to Chriſt and his waies, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That though the love of Chriſt manifeſted to a ſoul be that which ordinarily begets love in the ſoul to Chriſt, yet its poſſible there may be a real love to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is ſuch a manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now having minded ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particulars as to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition at that time when I did experience theſe things, I cannot altogether omit the kindneſs of God towards me in relation to perſecutions, which though it were but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44402:38"/> ſmall comparatively with ſome others, yet it was more than ſome met with, and it was that indeed which did require ſome ſtrength from the Lord to undergo it with comfort, in which he not being wanting to me, I Judge it ought not to be forgotten by me; and as I had comfort in it at that time preſent, ſo I am ſtill well ſatisfyed that I ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not as an evill doer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what I did then, was upon a conſcientious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, according to that light received. I could mention many particulars,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44402:39"/> but I forbear, heartily deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that it may never be laid to their charge. But this book being intended by me as a remembrancer of the former dealings of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, I think it not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether uſeles, as to remember the time I was in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; the manner how I was brought from it, ſo alſo the time when J was brought from it, and that was after the Biſhops were quite taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the beginning of the ſitting of the late Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. And here I deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member with thankfulneſs to God, that I was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared by the change of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44402:39"/> times and laws; For at that very time when the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> party, ſo called, began to reign, and J might have reignd with them, and enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſmiles from them, being convicted of a further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of truth J left them, and was content to become a ſcorn and a by-word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; Though J muſt confeſs J had much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from ſome of them all along, yet my ſufferings from that party were far more than the former. J could here mention many particulars, but J forbear, deſiring, as for the former, it may not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44402:40"/> be charged upon them; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe general hints I hope will be ſufficient to bring particulars to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, for theſe things ought not to be forgotten by me, becauſe in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them I find my heart much engaged in praiſes to God, and that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral waies; one way, and that not the leaſt, is, that God hath broken their power. For indeed I muſt needs ſay, that according to my obſervation and experience, I have ſeen as perſecuting a ſpirit in them as ever I did in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and they did appear as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44402:40"/> bitter, if not more, againſt ſuch as were called <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> than ever the Biſhops did againſt thoſe that were called <hi>Puritans,</hi> conſidering their time and power: For as their time was ſhort, ſo when their power was high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, there was alwaies a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which did a little aw them. I ſhall ſay no more of theſe things, but that as I deſire for ever to bleſſe the Lord in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, ſo I do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſire that God would deſtroy, or at leaſt keep un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, every perſecuting ſpirit,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44402:41"/> under what name or title ſoever called, till he is pleaſed to give them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:44402:41"/>
               <head>The third Note of Experience, How I was brought to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and believe the free Grace of God in the Gospell, and in believing to receive the aſſurance of the love of God.</head>
               <p>IN order to this experience I cannot omit to write ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning the reading of a book, by which as a means in the hand of God I received theſe never to be forgotten mercies. After I had livd about five or ſix years a ſtrict profeſſor, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry confident and ſettled upon the Lees of Legal Righteouſneſs, it pleaſed the Lord there came a man to the Town where I lived, whom though he was generally
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44402:42"/> reputed to be an honeſt man, yet he was much oppoſed as holding groſſe errors in his Judgement, and hearing many ſpeak very bitterly againſt him, I did much ponder it in my heart, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing (as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> ſpake concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 7. 50.) to judge before I heard, and therefore I reſolved to ſpeak with him, which accordingly I did, and found him ſpeaking ſuch things as I never heard before, which I then ignorantly judged to be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; the things he chiefly ſpake of, was about Free Grace, the nature of the Goſpel, and the New Covenant; and though I was not able to gain ſay the truth of what he ſpake, yet for fear of thoſe evill conſequences that a carnal heart might draw from them, I could not receive it. But after ſome diſcourſe, in much oppoſition, yet not bitter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44402:42"/> him, in the cloſe he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to lend me a book, in which (he ſaid) concerning the things he ſpake I might find better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction than he could give, being but weak in expreſſion; ſo I took it home with me, but being much afraid of error, I was at a great diſpute in my own ſpirit whether I ſhould read it or not; but fearing leſt I ſhould ſeem to ſhut my eyes againſt the light, at laſt I came to this reſult, that I would read it, but firſt ſet a part a day by faſting and prayer to ſeek the Lord, that what was truth in it I might embrace, and that he would keep and preſerve me from error (which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly I did) and finding the driſt and ſcope of the book was to exalt God, and lay low the Creature, I was much affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it, as alſo with ſome
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:44402:43"/> other particulars; but on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand theſe Miniſters (whoſe words were then as Oracles to me) did ſo much cry out againſt it, charging all to take heed of it, it being full of errors of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequences, that when I came about the middle of it I was ſo ſurpriſed with fear of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal liberty, meerly by their words, that I durſt read it no further, but ſent it home again, reſolving to ſtick to my old principles, and ſo reſolved I was, that I judged it my duty, and accordingly did praiſe the Lord, that I had eſcaped that ſnare and ſtumbling block which it was like to be to me, till about half a year after, theſe forementioned Miniſters not being ſatisfyed to ſpeak againſt thoſe books in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate only, but brought them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Pulpits reading particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:44402:43"/> paſſages, which as they read and applyed it, was contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ſenſe of it, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I thought they ſpake more than was true, which did occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion me to deſire the book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for my better ſatisfaction: but they not being allowed to be ſold at that time, it was hard to get any of them, but through mercy I got one, and then I found they did not deal faithfully, but did wreſt and draw falſe con ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences contrary to the driſt and ſcope of it, all which occaſioned ſerious thoughts in me, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring when I firſt read it I laid it aſide meerly from a ſpirit of fear and prejudice occaſioned by their words, and not that I was able to diſprove it from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture grounds; then remembring thoſe words of the Apoſtle, I <hi>Theſ. 5. 21. Try all things, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:44402:44"/> hold faſt that which is good,</hi> I thought it my duty to lay aſide all ſlaviſh fear and prejudice, and to try it exactly by the Scriptures, believing that as it was Gods way to try, ſo he would aſſiſt me in it, which he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to do, and as I read I began to be much affected, and I thought it was glad tidings and good news if it were true, but I thought it was too good to be true; for I could not then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that God was ſo free of his Chriſt, as to give him to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinners but to ſuch as were qualified, fitted, and prepared for him, or that the way to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was ſo eaſy as he ſeemed to mak it, for if it were ſo, then all that labour and travel which I had been a long time in, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which I could by no means yield to at that time. For as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44402:44"/> Chriſt once ſaid to the Jews that Publicans and Harlots enter into the Kingdom before them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 31. ſo truly I found it ſo hard to lay down my own legal righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and to ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of God by Faith, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 3. that I was like to ſtick here, when ſuch as were more profane might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the truth ſooner. But ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly weighing theſe with ſome other ſuch like Scriptures, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 4. and 5. 8. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. through grace I was in a great meaſure convinced and brought to ſee that I had been exceedingly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in my underſtanding and applying of Jeſus Chriſt, and whereas I thought I had attained a good degree of knowledge, I now ſaw my ſelf to be very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and muſt begin again to learn the firſt principles of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44402:45"/> of God, which to ſuffer ſo much loſs was very hard to me (at the firſt) but God was pleaſed by degrees to ſtrip me of all, and to ſhew me ſuch a beauty and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> above it, that I was made not only willing but joyous to lay down all at his feet, and I truſt could truly ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>That what was gain to me, I counted loſs for Chriſt, yea doubtleſs and I count all things but loſſe for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſs of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Chriſt, and be found in him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3: 7, 8, 9, &amp;c. and as God had exalted Chriſt to be a Prince and a Saviour, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 31. and had choſen him as the only excellent one in whom he had placed life and ſalvation for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:44402:45"/> people, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 18. ſo my ſoul did approve of it to be the moſt excellent way, and I truſt could truly ſay with the Spouſe, he is the chiefeſt of ten thouſand, ye he is one, and there is not another, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 12. and the more I came to apprehend the glory of the Goſpel in the free tenders and invitations of Chriſt to ſinners, the more ſtill I was affected with it, and did admire it, and ſeeing the tenders of grace ſo free, and the invitations ſo general that whoſoever would come might come and take of the water of life freely, <hi>Eſay</hi> 55. 1. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 17. and that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came to Chriſt he would in no wiſe caſt out, <hi>John</hi> 6. 37. by which word <hi>[come]</hi> I underſtood belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, verſ. 40. and then conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the nature of the covenant, that it is a covenant of grace free
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44402:46"/> and without all conditions on the creatures part, and that the conditions ſtand only between God and Chriſt, as I then under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. Through theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations I was not only encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, but the abounding love of Chriſt did compell and conſtrain me to caſt my ſelf upon him for life and ſalvation, in a way of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, and not in a way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; and to the praiſe of his grace as I deſire never to forget it. I did at this time receive the aſſurance of the love of God in believing the free and full par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all my ſins; That God had laid them all upon Chriſt, and beholding the travel of his ſoul, was ſatisfyed, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. 11. and well pleaſed with me in him <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 17. and that they were all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the wildernes of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44402:46"/> and buried in, Oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to that type of Chriſt, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16. 21, 22. and that they were waſhed away in his blood, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. 5. and that God would remember them no more, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 12. and 10. 17. Theſe Scriptures, with ſome others of the like nature, were by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſet home ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon my heart at that time, that truly I cannot expreſs the joyfulneſs and ſweetneſs of my condition, not being able to contain my ſelf from calling to others to tell them what God had done for my ſoul, how he had brought me out of bondage into the glorious liberty of adoption, and filled me with joy and peace in believing, yea with joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 8. and I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for a long time after I did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44402:47"/> to be almoſt continually ſpeaking or meditating of the glory of the free grace of God in the Goſpel, and of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and goodneſs to poor ſinners, and to me the chief of ſinners, for I know more evill by my ſelf than I do by any other, yet doubtleſs I can ſay as it was once ſaid of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel came not to me at that time in word only, but in power, and much aſſurance, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 5. and whereas formerly I thought that to receive ſuch a principle was the ready way to be looſe and carnal, I did believe that as ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification and ſanctification are inſeparable, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 13. and that as one end of Chriſts death was as well to redeem his people from all iniquity and the power of ſin, as from the puniſhment of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:44402:47"/> ſin, ſo the power of grace was more ſtrong and able to keep me from ſin, than all the legal bands and ſlaviſh fears in the world, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11. and though poſſibly I might meet with ſome temptations of that nature, yet to the praiſe of his grace, I can truly ſay I never found my heart more engaged for God and godlineſs, and more diſingaged from ſin, than now, which the Lord keep me ſo and all his, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observations">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:44402:48"/>
               <head>Some brief Obſervations from this third note of Experience.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, concerning my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in my former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, before I knew theſe things, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That perſons may be very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident on falſe grounds,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that it is not the confidence that makes the condition good, but the grounds of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For though ſtill I ſay I am inclined to own the work of converſion to be begun in me
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:44402:48"/> at that time before ſaid, by ſome accidental or provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential ſcatterings of the ſeed of the Goſpel, yet, through falſe teaching, thoſe ſeeds were ſo buried under the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of legal righteouſneſs, that there was a greater po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer required to blow off thoſe aſhes, and to carry on that work, than if it had never been begun, according to that foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned place, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 31. how hard then muſt it needs be to begin that work where there is only ſuch a righteouſneſs? from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:44402:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Legal righteouſneſſe (where the work of converſion is begun in a ſoul) is a great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the carrying on, and perfecting of that work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Concerning the manner of the dealings of God with me in the manifeſtation of his Love and Grace, which was at this time by reading, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed however God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to deal with others, yet with me, I cannot ſay but what I have received I have alwaies received by and through ſome means, from whence J obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is good to wait on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44402:49"/> God in the uſe of all means; for though the holy One of</hi> Iſrael <hi>is not limitted, yet ordinarily he works by means, and leaves no ground in holy Scripture to expect him out of means.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Concerning my idolizing thoſe fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Miniſters, being kept by it from reading or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any other doctrine but theirs, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is a dangerous thing to eſteem of perſons above what is meet, and to be implicitly lead by them in spiritual things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Concerning my not receiving the doctrine of Free Grace for fear of carnal
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44402:50"/> liberty, from thence I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſuch as are ignorant of the Free Grace of God are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to this miſtake, to think it the way to ſin, when indeed there is no true holineſs without it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, concerning its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo hard to me to lay down my own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c. and yet that I ſhould do it with ſo much Joy, when I ſaw cleerly the righteouſneſs of Chriſt to excell all, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That though it is a very hard
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44402:50"/> thing for perſons (eminent in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal righteouſneſs) to lay it down, and ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of God by faith, yet the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the tranſcendent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will make them do it with joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, Concerning my being ſo much affected with the Free Grace of God at my firſt receiving it, that I could not but declare it to others, from thence I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the glad tidings of the Gospel being applyed by the Spirit of Chriſt, ſo glads the heart, that when the ſoul firſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:44402:51"/> receives it its like fire that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, Concerning the effect of the Free Grace of God upon my heart, engaging me more to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and diſingaging me more from ſin, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That there is no engagement ſo strong to keep the ſoul from ſinning againſt God, as the Free Grace of God, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more endeers the heart to God; Yet doubtleſs where there is nothing but only the notion of it, there is the greateſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to Satan that can be, and uſually ſuch perſons are the worſt of all others.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:44402:51"/>
               <p>For though Goſpel bonds be the beſt to be tyed from ſin by, yet in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects its better to be tyed by Legal bonds than none at all; yet for Saints to be ſo tyed is not only carnal and below their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, but a great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Chriſt, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing of the Free Grace of God, which above all things ought to be exalted by us, as that alone by which we are truly exalted, and therefore ought to ly as the ſtrongeſt engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on Saints hearts to keep them from ſin; and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:44402:52"/> ſeeing all that we are, have, or ever ſhall have as to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs here, or glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, is all of Grace, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire for ever to admire it, and to live in the glory of it by faith; But this I find of all other the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Leſſon, yea ſo hard, that unto this day I have cauſe to complain of an unbelieving heart in many things, and I have often experienced that to bring over the heart to believe, and to keep it up in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, is no leſs than the mighty power and gift of God, <hi>John 6. 65. Phil</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:44402:52"/> 1. 29. <hi>Epheſi.</hi> 1. 19. yet in this I have ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, that I am kept by his power, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1. 5. and he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 13. 5. and as the Lord once ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> Though Satan ſhould deſire to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now me like Wheat, yet he hath prayed for me, and my Faith ſhall not fail; and though the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſon why ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do not believe, is for want of a clear under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Free Grace of God in the general
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44402:53"/> tenders of it to ſinners, yet all that have that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>John</hi> 12. 17. there were ſome whoſe hearts were hardned that they could not believe, and <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 41. it was ſaid of the Jews, they ſhould in no waies believe the Work of God, though a man declare it to them, that is to ſay, though they did underſtand it; and as Faith is wrought in the ſoul by God, ſo it is that by which we moſt honour him, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it is impoſſible
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44402:53"/> to pleaſe him. Faith works many waies, and it is an excellent thing to be ſtrong in faith, as we may ſee in thoſe Worthies, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> 11. It is the very life of Saints, <hi>Galatians</hi> 2. 20. and without it there is no life in them, <hi>John</hi> 6. 53. and as there is no life without it, ſo there is no life above it till grace be ſwallowed up in glory; For <hi>the juſt ſhall live by faith, Hebrews</hi> the 10. verſe 38. but though faith acts many waies, and about many things, yet it muſt alwaies act in free grace,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44402:54"/> and there is no room for it elſewhere: for when we go to exerciſe faith out of Free Grace, it is weak, and feeble, and ready to be turned aſide by the leaſt repulſe, but being there acted, all falls before it, as <hi>Dagon</hi> before the Ark, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin, law, or devill; Sin falls before it, as its an Inſtrument or means by which God purifies the heart, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 9. the law falls before it, as it takes the righteouſnes of Chriſt by which it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly fulfilled, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 4. Satan falls before it, as it is that by which we quench all his fiery darts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:44402:54"/> 6. 16. And as in this way I did at firſt receive the pardon of ſin, and ſo the knowledge of my intereſt in the Lord Jeſus, for Juſtification, Redemption and Salvation; So I have no other way (as I believe there is no other) by which I ſtill retain thoſe glorious pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, than in the ſame way in which I did firſt receive them, namely through grace by faith, not by any thing that is in me, or done by me, not by acts of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, works of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or ſubmiſſion to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, all which are too
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:44402:55"/> low and too little to keep up my union with God; but I deſire to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in theſe as they are commanded by God, and as they are fruits and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of faith, and through which I have communion with God and his people, which is a very great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, and I deſire that all Saints may ſo eſteem of them, and by no means ſlight them; but I do likewiſe deſire that none may eſteem of them above whats meet, as to glory in them, or to place that in them which is only peculiar to the Lord
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44402:55"/> Jeſus himſelf, who is our <hi>All in All, Coloſſi. 3. 11. Who of God is made unto us wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſs, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and redemption, that he that glorieth may glory in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 30, 31. And doubtleſs it is a great abuſe to Chriſt, and Ordinances, to glory in them, which we are ſubiect to do, when we live not in the beholding of him through the riches of his grace by Faith, which as I ſaid before, is the higheſt life, and ſo far as I have experienced the excellency and glory of it, I can ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I deſire to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:44402:56"/> know nothing but Chriſt and him crucified,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 2. <hi>and God forbid that I ſhould glory in any thing ſave in the croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 1. 14. I may further ſay of my experience in this matter, as <hi>David</hi> of the Sword of <hi>Goliah, There is none like it,</hi> 1 Sam. 21. 9. or as the Apoſtle ſaid to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> That <hi>though they had ten thouſand Inſtructors, yet not many Fathers;</hi> ſo though I had ten thouſand expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, yet I <hi>have none like this;</hi> For all muſt cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter here, and without
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44402:56"/> this all is nothing; And herein me thinks the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and excellency of the life of faith in Free Grace doth much appear, in that the weak and ſtrong Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an do both meet and are ſatisfyed in it, the higheſt capacity may be exerciſed in learning more of it, and yet the loweſt may reach it, ſo as to live and have ſtrong conſolation in it, and Fools ſhall not erre therein, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the 35. chapter, verſe 8. This is that new and living way by the blood of Jeſus, <hi>Hebrews</hi> ch. 10. verſes 19, 20.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:44402:57"/> the richeſt and higheſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that ever was beſtowed on the children of men, to him therefore be glory and praiſe for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:44402:57"/>
               <head>The fourth Note of Experience, how I was convinced and brought to ſubmit to Baptiſm and Church-fellowſhip commanded by Christ.</head>
               <p>BEing through mercy now well ſatisfied in point of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, Redemption, and Salvation, though I had nothing to do to be ſaved, yet I had much to do to glorifie God in relation to Sanctification and Obedience; but notwithſtanding all my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer experience in point of Faith, I was very ignorant of Baptiſm, and all other duties and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces relating to the viſible practice of Believers, onely I had ſome dark apprehenſions of ſeparation, and a Church way, by reaſon of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44402:58"/> which I had thoughts to join with ſome who were called <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents;</hi> but conſidering how I had formerly been miſtaken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout things of that nature, I was not haſty to practiſe it, untill I was better ſatisfied, being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what at a loſs about it; then after ſome time I heard of Baptiſm, though I had no acquaintance with any that practiſed it, yet knowing there were ſuch, did occaſion me to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures about it, and by ſeveral places in the <hi>Acts,</hi> with that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. I was in a great meaſure convinced that Baptiſm of Believers was an Ordinance of Chriſt, and that there could be no true Church without it, and that Baptizing of Infants is that for which I could find no ground in Scripture; and by degrees I was ſo fully ſatisfied in it, and I
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44402:58"/> thought the Scriptures were ſo plain and clear for it, that I did much wonder at my own igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that I ſhould be a profeſſor ſo long, and ſo frequent in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Scripture, and yet ignorant of that which was ſo plainly therein expreſt; then coming to <hi>London</hi> to that end, namely to be inſtructed in the waies of God more perfectly, not knowing the like means elſe where, I went many times to hear in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt, by which, through the great bleſſing of God, I was more and more ſatisfied about it; yet notwithſtanding all this, by hearkning to the deluſions of my own heart, and Satans inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I met with many inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and temptations that kept me from my duty, at leaſt one whole year after; ſome of thoſe temptations were theſe:</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:44402:59"/>
               <p>Firſt, I thought though the Saints of old did practiſe theſe things, yet as they were now practiſed it was ſome kind of bondage, and below the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the Goſpell to be tyed to a particular people, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in relation to hearing; for I thought I ſhould not forbear hearing ſome particular men, (who were not in the order of the Goſpell) that formerly I u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to hear.</p>
               <p>A ſecond thing that hindred me was the failings and miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of ſome particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then in the Churches.</p>
               <p>A third hinderance was, I thought it my liberty to do or not do it.</p>
               <p>A fourth hinderance was in relation to Perſecution, I judged I ſhould not be fit to ſuffer for it (though a truth of Chriſt)
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44402:59"/> untill all thoſe Scruples were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
               <p>Theſe, with others of the like nature, were the groundleſſe thoughts that kept me from my duty; but though kept back by theſe for a time, yet I had ſuch ſtrong convictions that I could not leave it ſo, but was much endevouring after ſatisfaction, and in the uſe of means God was pleaſed to ſatisfy me; but by reaſon of perſecution there was no Church I knew of, but onely in <hi>London,</hi> and therefore I could not immediately do it; but being to be married ſoon after, I was to live in <hi>London,</hi> and then I reſolved to ſubmit to this Ordinance of Chriſt; but when I came to <hi>London,</hi> I heard all kind of preachers, one of which preached a ſtrange kind of doctrine much notion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44402:60"/> which bred ſuch a confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in my heart that I knew not what to do, by which I was again hindered from my duty, being willing to try that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, I not having heard the like before, it being full of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing words of mans wiſdome, which I did with as much diligence try for ſome time, examining the Scriptures about it, as ever I did any doctrine, but could find nothing in it but confuſion, a meer ſound of words, ſome of thoſe bigge ſwelling words of vanity ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Jude 16. 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 18. ſo, through mercy, I left it, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped that ſnare, which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to remember to the praiſe of God. Then I reſolved to proſecute my former purpoſe in relation to thoſe duties before mentioned, yet ſtill lingring in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:44402:60"/> 
                  <hi>Babylon</hi> till the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a ſtretched-out arm, and cleer voice, to bring to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thoſe words in the 22. chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> verſe 6. <hi>Ariſe and be baptized, why tarryeſt thou?</hi> and (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) for ſome daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whatever I was doing, thoſe words were much in my thoughts, then I began to take particular notice of it, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to my own condition, whether I was able to give a reaſon why I tarried, the Lord having removed all my ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and anſwered all my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions, and ſpeaking of it to my Husband, who was then much in the ſame condition, I remember we had ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about it, and the reſult was, that the next firſt day we
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:44402:61"/> would go to the Church (where we had often heard) and declare what God had done for us in the great work of converſion, deſiring alſo to obey him in all his commands, which accordingly we did, and gave them full ſatisfaction, and the week following were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized and added to the Church, being ſweetly ſatisfyed and comforted therein; and as for my former ſcruples I was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled no more with them, and in particular as to hearing out of the Church, I never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it ſince, but God was pleaſed, and ſtill is, to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy me with the fatneſs of his houſe, feeding me with green paſtures there; and ſitting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of Chriſt, his Fruit is ſweet to my taſt;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:44402:61"/> which the LORD grant I may be found ſo doing, as he hath commanded, until his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="observations">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:44402:62"/>
               <head>Some brief Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon this fourth Note of Experience.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Concerning thoſe thoughts, that though I had nothing to do to be ſaved, yet I had much to do to glorify God, &amp;c. from thence I obſerve.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That as it is the duty of all that have received the Grace of God to be active for his Glory, ſo it is the nature of Grace to teach and engage Saints to do the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Concerning
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:44402:62"/> my ignorance of Baptiſm, and other Ordinances, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Experience in point of Faith, from thence I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That perſons may have much Experience in point of privilege, and yet be ignorant of their duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As indeed we are more apt to learn the one than the other.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Concerning my ignorance of that which is ſo plainly expreſſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from thence I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That light diſcovers dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:44402:63"/> and though Truth be never ſo plainly expreſſed, yet ignorance cannot apprehend it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Concerning thoſe interruptions and temptations that kept me from my duty, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That naturally we are ſo averſe to duty, that we are a long time before we know our duties, and when we know them we are ſubject to be kept from doing them by very tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles; and that it is Satans policy, if he cannot keep us from knowing our duties, to caſt ſtumbling-blocks in our way if poſſible to keep us us from doing them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:44402:63"/>
               <p>2. I obſerve, <hi>That though Chriſts yoak be eaſie, yet we are hardly brought to put it on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, Concerning the firſt hinderance, That I thought it ſome Bondage to be in a Church, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That through ignorance of the nature of Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we are too ſubject to think that Bondage which is not only Liberty but a great Privilege.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, Concerning the ſecond hinderance, which was the unſuitable walkings of ſome particular perſons then in the Church, from thence I obſerve.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:44402:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Conſideration of our stumbling at the failings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhould make us carefull leſt we occaſion others to ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, Concerning the third hinderance, That it was our liberty whether we would walk in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and ſubmit to Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances or not, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That we are naturally ſo addicted to liberty, that we are many times ready to caſt off all obedience, and to look on the Ordinances of Chriſt as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eighthly, Concerning
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:44402:64"/> the fourth hinderance, Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſt I had not faith e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſuffer for it, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That diſtruſtfull thoughts of future mercies many times keep us from improving preſent mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninethly, Concerning thoſe Convictions, that though I was ſcrupled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout truth, yet could not leave it ſo, but endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after full ſatisfaction, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſtrong Convictions are not eaſily put out, and where grace is predominant, there will be an endeavour not to ſmother
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:44402:65"/> but to anſwer them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tenthly, Concerning that other hinderance by ſtrange doctrine, from thence I obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That as faith comes by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo there may be a hearing that tends to the prejudice of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſuch I conclude is all hearing out of the way of God, though ſome more, ſome leſſe; I mean pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick hearing out of the Church of God; and though ſome do iudge it their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and privilege ſo to do, I muſt needs confeſs I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo iudge: For though
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:44402:65"/> poſſibly glorious things may be ſpoken, yet what privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege can it be for Saints to hear glorious things, where there is no promiſe of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may ſay as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, of ſpeaking in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue, I had wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hear five words from a true Miniſtery, or in a Church of Chriſt, where he hath promiſed his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and preſence, than five thouſand elſewhere, though I deſire in a perſonal way to own and embrace all or any appearance of God where ever I find it, and can
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44402:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> upon that account truly ſay, I do much reſpect, love, and delight in ſome who are not yet come up to the true worſhip of Chriſt in his Church, but I muſt be true to my principles, I cannot ſee how we that are, according to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ioyned to the Lord, and his Church, by which we hold out to the world a viſible profeſſion of his name, and a ſeparation from all falſe waies of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which in our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples we judge them who are not rightly conſtituted with us according to the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:44402:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> appointment and practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to be no other, I ſay I cannot ſee how we can meet with them in their publique worſhip, to hear their Miniſters, or in any other ſpiritual duty, but it is a croſſing our own principles: As thus, they own themſelves true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Miniſters of Chriſt, the ignorant world knoweth not but they are ſo, we by our preſence being ſilent do ſay the ſame, though in our Judgement we cannot ſo own them, which is a plain contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:44402:67"/> in our principles; we ſay they are not Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Miniſters of Chriſt, by our practice we ſay they are, as hath been minded.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction of our own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſo it hath had ſuch effects, which are too vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and remains unto this day. I muſt confeſs, in my moſt ſerious thoughts I have wondered what ſhould be the reaſon that any in the houſe of God ſhould deſire to be elſewhere: I am ſure there is no reaſon to be given for it, neither from Scripture, nor expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; therefore I conclude,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:44402:67"/> its either from ignorance, &amp; ſo perſons in their practice croſs their own principles and not know it; or elſe its from corrupt principles; or elſe they are <hi>overcome</hi> by ſome violent temptations. As to the 1. of theſe, I truſt there are not many in the houſe of God ſo ignorant. As to the 2. it is the deſire of my ſoul, that God would reprove &amp; ſhew them the evill of ſuch princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and recover them out of ſuch ſnares. As to the 3. Let them take heed leſt having put their hand to the plow, and looking back, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unfit for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:44402:68"/> of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 62. and let them likewiſe take heed of pleaſing men, or halting between two opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but <hi>if God be God follow him, if</hi> Baal <hi>follow him,</hi> 1 Kings 28 21. This may ſeem harſh language to ſome, but I am ſatisfyed that what I have written hath not been from a cenſorious ſpirit, to Judge of the final State of any, or to queſtion the grace of God in any, where it doth appear in the leaſt meaſure, and therefore let none ſay that becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not own any to be true Churches or Miniſters of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:44402:68"/> Chriſt, but ſuch as are in the ſame order with us, that therefore I ſay there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of God or Truth in them, or that none ſhall be ſaved but our ſelves, or that we love none but thoſe of our own Judgement, which if any do ſo think, or ſpeak of us, it is a very great miſtake; for if I may ſpeak for others, as I have already ſaid, I do upon a godly account love, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſome who are not in our Churches, and do wait for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe glorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes when they and we ſhall
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:44402:69"/> have a pure language, &amp; ſhall call upon the Lord, &amp; ſerve him with one conſent, and when we ſhall have one heart and one way, <hi>and there ſhall be one Lord, and his name one, Zeph. 3. 9. Jer. 32. 39. Zach.</hi> 14. 9. In the mean time, Let none un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of waiting for the accompliſhment of ſuch promiſes as theſe, grow cold, and indifferent in the great things of God: For none can truly wait for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of Promiſes, but ſuch as do wait in a cloſe walking with God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that meaſure of light received, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:44402:69"/> ſo thoſe that have but a little of the knowledge of God, let them follow on to know the Lord, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6. 3. and let thoſe that are in the faith, earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for it, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. and ſuch as are in Goſpel Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, let them ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one mind, ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 27. and let every one that names the name of Chriſt, depart from iniquity, 2 <hi>Timothy</hi> 2. 19. and thoſe that love the Lord, hate evil, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 97. 10. And as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that none may ſlight,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:44402:70"/> grow cold, or indifferent in the great things of God, under a pretence of waiting for high enjoyments or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, which ſhall be in the later daies; ſo I deſire likewiſe that none may plead againſt the Truth, under a pretence of Love, as many do in theſe daies, labouring to confound light with darkneſs, truth with error, and to make an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, where God hath made none. Let ſuch know, that true ſpiritual love, as it is wrought in the heart by the Spirit of God, ſo it is bounded within the limits
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44402:70"/> of Truth, Love and Truth go hand in hand; it is ſo fixed upon God, that it Loves all in and for him; ſpiritual Love muſt have a ſpiritual object, and as the obiect is more or leſs viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo is that Love, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not love every thing alike, nay it works as well by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of evill as approving that which is good, <hi>Pſa. 101. Pſa. 97. 10. Rev. 2. 6. Pſa.</hi> 119. 122, 128. It loves that which God loves, and hates that which he hates; it loves the Word of God, the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, and the people of God, and hates all that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44402:71"/> is in oppoſition to theſe, it rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 6. This is true ſpiritual love, in which we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive every truth, and by which faith worketh, 2 <hi>Theſ. 2. 10. Gal.</hi> 5. 6. and I dare affirm, whatever perſons may pretend of ſpiritual love that is not of this nature, it is a meer deluſion, and that all that fear the Lord ought to take heed of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:44402:71"/>
               <head>The fift Note of Experience, concerning Notions, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Spiritualities, in which Satan transforms himſelf into an Angel of light; and how far I was deceived by it, and how the Lord was pleaſed to recover me out of it.</head>
               <p>BEing now through much mercy brought out of <hi>Babylon</hi> into <hi>Sion,</hi> to partake of thoſe dainties which the Lord hath prepared for his people, there Satan, that grand Enemy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, who <hi>goeth about like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lion ſeeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 8. envies my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and waites his opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to catch me as a fiſh in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:44402:72"/> the water, covering his hook with a bait of myſtery and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality, who though I had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped him in all his former ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances as a devill, yet now transforms himſelf into an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of light, if it were poſſible for ever thereby to beguile and deceive me; knowing that thoſe that are ſo deceived are the fitteſt Agents to promote his Kingdome, and that many times he prevailes this way when he can prevail no other way, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons to that by degrees through corrupt principles, which they would have trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the thoughts of before they had ſuch principles; but God was pleaſed not onely to keep me from ſuch things, but alſo diſcover to me the way by which perſons are brought to ſuch things, that ſo to the praiſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:44402:72"/> of his Grace, I might avoid thoſe waies, and alſo forewarn others to avoid them likewiſe. But before I was brought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Satan under theſe veiles, by hearkning to the voice of the Tempter (in the thoughts of which I deſire ever to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the preſence of God) I was deceived and beguiled by him in ſome particular things, and that after this manner; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had lived ſome time in <hi>London,</hi> walking with the Church, in the practice of the Goſpel, it pleaſed God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move our habitation into the Country, where we had not that privilege, and after a while, (my Husband being in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) it occaſioned our often mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving into ſeveral places, where we found not only particular perſons, but whole Churches
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:44402:73"/> very much corrupted, owning &amp; practiſing ſtrange things, though under plauſible terms and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual pretences, by which a while after they were broken and ſcattered, leaving the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of truth in the practice of the Ordinances of Chriſt, ſome under one notion, and ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another, ſo that it was hard to find in thoſe parts one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon that had ſound principles, much leſs a whole Church where there was a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Miniſtery, and a wiſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by reaſon of which I began by degrees to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what confuſed in Judgement; and truly, when I conſider thoſe things, and what temptations I was expoſed to at that time, I do not wonder I was ſo confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but I rather wonder at the mercy of God that I was not
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44402:73"/> ſwallowed up with confuſion, as many were in thoſe daies, for though I was weak in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and by thoſe things ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what confuſed, yet I do not know that in two or three years time I had received any corrupt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; but afterward being with a people where Satan had trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed himſelf into an Angell of light, I think I may ſay in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree, under terms of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, Spirit, waiting upon God, and ſuch like, by them I was beguiled and deceived in ſome particular things, though never in the height of that which was practiſed by them; the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars about which I was deceived were chiefly theſe three or four.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Concerning godlineſs being a myſtery, that it did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of ſomething within, and not of ſomething without, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:44402:74"/> and that the Saints were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect life and Salvation from a Chriſt within, and not from a Chriſt without.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that Saints were not to do duties by or from a command without, but from a command within, and that the word Command in Scripture was not a command to them till they had a word within them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that as to the time of doing duties they were to wait for the movings of the Spirit to carry them forth to it, and this they called waiting for a power, and till they had ſuch a power, they were to do nothing but ſit ſtill and wait, and this not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in private duties, but in the Church alſo, not owning any Miniſtery by way of gifts or office, but to come together, and there fit and wait till they
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:44402:74"/> had a power, and then to ſpeak, whether men or women.</p>
               <p>In theſe particulars, which carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſuch a face or ſhew of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality, I was corrupted, but did never fully own them in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor practice; and for ſuch principles as (I thought) did lead to looſneſs, either in matter of conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion, or in ſlighting the <hi>Churches</hi> or ordinances of Chriſt, I did alwaies oppoſe them, though I believe ſuch princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples do naturally follow the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but I did not then diſcern it, they being covered over with ſuch Angel-like appearances; And as to that principle of wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, though I did own it in Judgement more fully than any of theſe other, yet I could neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come up to it in my practice in private duties, but by reaſon of ſome convictions ſtill remaining
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:44402:75"/> in me I could not ſtay ſo long from duty till I had ſuch a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but did frequently go to du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty when I had it not, though ſometimes I thought I had it. But in the preſence of others I did not appear in duty, but when I thought I had that power, though I never did ſo appear but in one place for a ſhort ſeaſon, in doing which I thought I had commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God; but I do believe it was no ſuch thing, but a meer Spirit of deluſion: Firſt becauſe I know no Scripture-ground for ſuch a practice; and ſecondly from the conſideration of the ſad fruit I had by it, for after a little time I began to loſe my peace, and was very much troubled, having little or no communion with God, nor ſcarce any thing to ſpeak to or for God, and ſo confounded I was in my own
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:44402:75"/> ſpirit, that I knew not what to do, and ſpeaking of it to ſome, and thoſe not a few, they labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to perſwade me it was a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of God, and that the Saints after they were brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> muſt be in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs before they come to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and that the end of God in bringing them there was, that he might ſpeak comfortably to them, and therefore I was not to be troubled, but to be quiet, fit ſtill, and wait, and not to ſtir the Lord till he pleaſed; this did not at all ſatisfy me, but I continued in a very ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and one thing more by the way I cannot forget, and that is, that while I was in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I never was ſo troubled with temptations as I was at that time; One temptation which I
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:44402:76"/> was troubled with many years before, I was kept from until at this time, which now was more violent than at firſt, as indeed thoſe things naturally lead to ſuch temptations, which tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the ſame expreſſed in the beginning of the book page 25.</p>
               <p>This was the ſad fruit of my ſtraying from the pure waies of truth, which as I deſire ever to own with ſhame to my ſelf, ſo likewiſe conſidering the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I was expoſed to, and the little means I had to forewarn and keep me from ſuch things, I deſire for ever to bleſs the Lord that I ſtrayed no further; that though in <hi>theſe</hi> things I had much forgotten him, yet he was pleaſed to remember me, and ſhewed me the evil and danger of theſe notions, and reſtored me to thoſe former joies that once I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:44402:76"/> had in him, and made that which was intended by Satan to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw me, to be of great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to me, which he was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do after this manner.</p>
               <p>Having ſome occaſion to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a paſſage on the Sea from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> in which condition it pleaſed the Lord to reprove me by the raging waves of the Sea, and tempeſtuous ſtorms, then began my trouble to increaſe, but not ſo much from that which was without, as from ſomething within, the waves of the Sea not beating ſo faſt on the Ship, as the waves of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did ariſe in my heart, being in a very much-troubled diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyed condition, not finding my heart willing to ſubmit to God, neither indeed knowing how to behave my ſelf towards him in relation to the preſent
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:44402:77"/> trouble, all which was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by thoſe corrupt principles, being at a great loſs whether I ſhould now pray or wait for a power, not being ſenſible of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other power at that time but what was from the preſent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to put me upon it; but in this trial I was glad to betake my ſelf to my former principles, the Lord bringing to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that command and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50. 15. by which I was encouraged to cry to God, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I could not, nor durſt not forbear; for ſtill owning my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in God, by which I was made capable of prayer, I could not anſwer that, with ſuch other like Scriptures, as 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 17. &amp;c. but yet notwithſtanding I was diſſatisfyed about it, that noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of waiting carrying ſuch a ſhew of ſpirituality, I could not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:44402:77"/> eaſily let it go, but yet this try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all had ſo ſhaken it, that I did begin much to queſtion it, and alſo thoſe other notions of the like nature; then it pleaſed the Lord to bring us ſafe to Land, through which mercy I had ſome little communion with God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to ſpeak of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in delivering us from that danger, but through that diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, which ſtill remained in me about theſe notions, it was interrupted again, and my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved had withdrawn himſelf, and I was very much troubled, not knowing where to reſt, nor what to do, but notwithſtanding I did begin much to queſtion thoſe things from that trial I had of them on the Sea, yet I was more inclined to them than to truth, for ſome time, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to that of prayer, and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:44402:78"/> three or four times after I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member in diſcourſe with ſome friends I did a little plead for them, which though it was my ſin ſo to do, I did not then know it, but muſt needs ſay I did as ſimply and ſincerely aim at doing the wil of <hi>God</hi> in all thoſe things, as ever I did in any thing, and therefore though Satan had ſo beguiled me, yet I obtained mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, becauſe I did it ignorantly; but my trouble and want of communion with God did ſtill increaſe, inſomuch that I was ſcarce able to bear my burthen, and ſpeaking of it to my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who was at that time much in the ſame condition, I remember, amongſt many words he ſpake, ſome were to this purpoſe, That ſeeing we were in ſuch a condition, and at ſuch a loſs, it was beſt to ſpeak
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:44402:78"/> but little, that as we did but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good, we might do but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle harm, which I did well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, and after that I ſpake little for or againſt any thing till I was better ſatisfyed; then being ſo truly in a day of adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, according to that counſel of the Wiſe man in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 14. I ſate down ſeriouſly to conſider what might be the cauſe of my being in ſo ſad and ſtrange a condition; Through which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration by degrees I came to ſee and conclude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that certainly there was ſomething amiſs in my Judgement as to thoſe notions, beginning clearly to diſcern they did ſo oppoſe and contradict my former received principles, that they could not ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but if one was true, the other was falſe, and that I muſt leave the one or the other; for
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:44402:79"/> though I had received the new, I could never fully quit the old, neither in Judgement nor pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Then I was reſtleſs in my deſire for three or four daies, to know which of the two were truth, oft times earneſtly beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of God that he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the controverſie, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to me which was according to his mind, and which not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully ſatisfied that but one of them could be truth; then it pleaſed the Lord to put me upon a particular examination what grounds I had in Scripture, and what experience I had of both, &amp; in reading and examining my Scripture-grounds, I began to diſcern a great inclination in my heart to the former principles, finding (I thought) the Scripture very full and plain for them, but nothing for the other, but what
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:44402:79"/> was from ſome dark myſterious interpretations, which were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doubtfull; and for my own experience, I did remember, and was conſtrained to acknowledge, that in receiving and keeping cloſe to the fotmer, I had joy and peace, and much ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and communion with God, but ſince I received the other, the Lord had as it were hid his face from me, and I was filled with confuſion and diſtraction, and the remembrance of that tryall I had of them upon the Sea did very much help me now to ſee the falſity of them, that in a time of tryal I durſt not ſtick to them; as indeed I plainly ſaw that I could never ſtick to them ſo as to anſwer them fully in my practice, unleſs I ſhould have laid aſide the appearance of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, &amp; have been very profane:
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:44402:80"/> the conſideration of which, with ſome other evill conſequences, which I ſaw cleerly did natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend thoſe things, was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means by which the Lord was pleaſed to recover me from them, and to diſcover Satan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his veil to me, how by theſe things he did intend, if the Lord had not prevented him, to have ſtript me of all my hopes; and in particular as to that of being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a Chriſt within, and not by a Chriſt without, the Lord was pleaſed to ſhew me that it was quite another thing differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Goſpel, and that it was attended with this evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, even to overthrow the whole Goſpel, and to deny the Lord that bought them; at the thoughts of which my ſoul did tremble, and that if he ſhould have prevailed here, all my hopes
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:44402:80"/> were gone; for I could not, nor durſt not reſt on any thing in my ſelf as a ground of hope for life and ſalvation; but on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand concerning my hope in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Goſpel, I could tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay of that as <hi>Peter</hi> did, <hi>John 6. 68. Lord whither ſhall we go? thou haſt the words of eternal life,</hi> ſo whither ſhould I go from the Goſpel? there are the words of eternal life, there is all my reſt and hopes in the Lord Jeſus through the Goſpel, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reſolved in the ſtrength of Chriſt to ſtick to this, and leave the other. Then ſecondly as to that of waiting for a power to pray, and that there was no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand but from within, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both theſe the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhew me that it was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his mind, but a meer
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:44402:81"/> invention of Satan, by degrees to draw me from my duties, and that it was attended with this evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, even to ſlight the Scriptures and commands of God, and to expoſe the Soul to Satans deceivings, to walk by the imaginations of their own hearts, inſtead of the motions of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and alſo it brings the ſoul into great uncertainties, which the truth never doth; but on the other hand to do dueties in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the authority and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God in Scripture, and to pray at all times as we have opportunities, having received a principle of grace by which we are made capable of prayer, I ſaw this was a cleer and ſound truth, not being atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with any evill conſequence, nor bringing the ſoul into ſtraits and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties, but rather gives en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:44402:81"/> in every condition, and therefore I deſired likewiſe to keep cloſe to theſe, and leave the other; but oh the joy and comfort that was in my Soul at this return! I cannot expreſs it, but this I ſay, it was to me as life from the dead. And as I was bleſſing, praiſing, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord for his unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goodneſs to me, my Huſband, having been ſome time from me, came home, to whom I did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my condition, and what the Lord had done for me, who, as I have formerly hinted, was much in the ſame condition with me, who alſo declared that he had in a meaſure received the like mercy, which did much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my joy. Then I remember he deſir'd we might ſeek the Lord by prayer, and praiſe his holy name for theſe and all his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:44402:82"/> In which duty the Lord was pleaſed ſo abundantly to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelf to us, thereby te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying his acceptance of us, that for a while we ſate in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither of us ſcarce being able to ſpeak for tears; and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it was ſuch a mercy that I truſt we ſhall for ever admire it, at leaſt in theſe five particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that God ſhould deal ſo faithfully with us in relation to his promiſe, that when we were ready to turn to the right hand or to the left, he cauſed us to hear his voice behind us, ſaying, <hi>this is the way, walk in it, Eſay</hi> 30. 21.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that when we were ſtraying from truth, that the Lord ſhould keep us that we ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no further, that we did not, run to the hight of thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, denying the Churches,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:44402:82"/> and Ordinances of Chriſt, and blaſpheming the truth, as very many did in thoſe times, even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord that bought them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the Lord ſhould deal ſo fatherly and tenderly in his reſtoring of us, that it was not by any extraordinary afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or chaſtiſement, neither were we at any time a trouble to the Churches, or grief to any Saint I know of.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that the Lord ſhould be pleaſed to bring us off ſo clearly from thoſe things; for many are brought off from them, and yet there is ſtill ſo much confuſion remaining up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſpirits, that it is hard to diſcern whether they are brought off or no.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, that the Lord ſhould vouchſafe this mercy to both of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:44402:83"/> us, &amp; that at one &amp; the ſame time; and that at our return he ſhould manifeſt ſuch a ſweet acceptance of us, melting our hearts into tears of joy, to our mutual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the Lord, and in each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and ſo that ſtream of our hearts being now turned from running after lying vanities, the Lord was pleaſed to re-eſtabliſh and confirm us every day more and more in the truth, turning this ſad (yet bleſſed) Experience, to his praiſe, and our great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, the remembrance of which I truſt ſhall be a mercy that ſhall ſtand us in ſtead at times of need, whiles we live; which the Lord grant it may be ſo, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and praiſe of his great name and our own peace and happines in himſelf. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="considerations">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:44402:83"/>
               <head>Some further Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons relating to this part of my Experience, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which I judge ſo conſiderable I cannot omit the reviewing of it.</head>
               <p>AND the Lord grant I may review it daily, ſo as to have my heart rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to an holy admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the goodneſs and faithfulneſs of God towards me in it, and that it may all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies lie as a ſtrong engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon my heart to love and obey him in all things,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:44402:84"/> which in conſideration of his unſpeakable mercy is but my reaſonable ſervice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1. And as I deſire for ever to bleſs the Lord that he was pleaſed to deliver me from theſe deceits, ſo it ſhall be my prayer that all the Lords people may be delivered from them, and that the rather, becauſe I am perſwaded that errors of that nature are the worſt of all others, and doubtleſs they are the greateſt myſtery of iniquity that ever Satan had on foot in the world. But becauſe I am not willing to paſs my ſentence without
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:44402:84"/> grounds, and becauſe every thing that is reproved is made manifeſt by the light, and that which doth make manifeſt is light, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 13. I deſire, according to that light of truth which God hath given to me, farther to conſider, not only in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral that thoſe kind of errors are the worſt of all others, but more particularly how they are ſo.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I conceive they are the worſt of all others, in that they do naturally tend and lead to the higheſt degree of evill, and that both as they take with gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:44402:85"/> hearts, and as they take with carnal hearts; Firſt, as they take with gracious hearts they do naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt the ſouls communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to great temptations, bringing it to ſtraits and extremities, and into the greateſt confuſion that can be poſſible, ſo far as they prevail; and for the truth of this, beſides my own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, I appeal to any experienced Chriſtian if it be not ſo.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as they take with carnal hearts they lead by degrees to the greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:44402:85"/> both in a ſpiritual and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſenſe; for ſuch hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not being ſeaſoned wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> grace, they run from on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> notion to another, till they run ſo high as to ſtand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly in oppoſition to Chriſt and his Goſpel: For when they come to be confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and at a loſs in their Judgements, and meet with ſuch Temptations, which thoſe errors naturally lead to, they are overcome by them, and under a pretence of living above Ordinances they deny the Ordinances of Chriſt, and by degrees the whole Word of God,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:44402:86"/> calling it literal and carnal, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d under a pretence of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>uality, blaſpheme the name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Chriſt, calling him <hi>A fleſhly Chriſt,</hi> and ſo <hi>denying the Lord that bought them, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 1. and going againſt ſuch ſtrong convictions and cleer manifeſtations of light and knowledge, as ſome have done, doubtleſs they have fallen into that unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſin expreſſed in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. and ſo come at laſt to jeer and ſcoff at all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of godlineſs; and it makes way for the higheſt degree of wickedneſs alſo in a civil ſenſe, <hi>having giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:44402:86"/> themſelves up to work all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs with greedineſs,</hi> Eſay 4. 19. and ſo breaking all bonds, though <hi>they had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the pollutions of the world through the knowledge of our Lord, yet being again entangled therein, their latter end is worſe than the beginning,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 20. according to that <hi>Mat. 13. 43, 44, 45. When the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through dry places, ſeeking reſt, and findeth none, then he returns, and taketh ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven other ſpirits more wicked than himſelf, and they enter in and dwell there, and the laſt state of that man is worſe than
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:44402:87"/> the beginning;</hi> he is now far more wicked than ever: this is the nature, and theſe are the effects of thoſe kind of notions as they take with carnal hearts; and that it is ſo, I appeal to the times in which we live, if we have not ſeen it ſo with many who had eſcaped the pollutions of the world, and that evil ſpirit ſeemed to be gone out of them, and they have made large profeſſions of the power of truth in their hearts, but they are turned with the dog to his vomit, and with the ſow that was waſht to her wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:44402:87"/> in the myre, glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their ſhame, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that without any reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, which they would have trembl'd at the thoughts of before they had thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and if any ſhould have propheſied ſuch things of them, they would have ſaid as <hi>Hazael</hi> did to <hi>Eliſha, Is thy ſervant a dog that he ſhould do ſuch things?</hi> 2 Kings 8. 13. Theſe things conſidered, is a ſufficient ground for me to conclude, that errors of that nature are the worſt of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, as they are the worſt in that they natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:44402:88"/> lead to the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of evil, ſo they are the worſt in that they are the greateſt myſtery of iniquity, ſo more deceiving than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that they are ſo, it will appear, if we conſider, firſt, how covertly, and under how many veils Satan comes in them, beguiling and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving with the moſt plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, ſpiritual, Angel-like glorious appearances that can be expreſſed, and as it ſaid of the falſe Prophets, <hi>Mat. 7. 15. They come in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves;</hi> ſo it may be truly ſaid of thoſe notions,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:44402:88"/> they are clothd with glorious and Chriſt-like appearances, but when we ſee to the botom of them, they differ as much from Chriſt, as a ravening wolf from a ſheep: for they do not only beguile and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in that they are not what they ſeem or pretend to be, and in that they do not give what they promiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> high lights, glory, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, immediate commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the father, &amp; ſuch like; But as a ravening wolf, ſo far as they prevail, they devour and deſtroy by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees all appearance of good, and therefore the Apoſtle
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:44402:89"/> calls them perverſe things, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 30. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. they are called <hi>damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> and <hi>pernitious waies,</hi> and <hi>big ſwelling words of vanity,</hi> ver. 18. words that will <hi>eat as doth a Cancker, 2 Tim.</hi> 2. 17. And becauſe they are ſo apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a myſtery of iniquity, that is (I conceive) the reaſon why the Apoſtle gives ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, and doth ſo often forewarn the Saints to take heed of them: for queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs they are the very ſame errors which are mentioned in thoſe Scriptures, and we may know them to be ſo, in that they carry the very ſame
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:44402:89"/> badges and marks expreſſed in thoſe Scriptures, as</p>
               <p>Firſt, in relation to the riſe of them, which was not from the falſe Prophets of the world, but from falſe Brethren in the Church, and others ſuch like, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed an oppoſition to thoſe falſe Prophets; and the place and people among whom they were moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing, was not with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſons in the world, but among knowing perſons, and in the Churches of Chriſt; all which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame expreſt in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Scriptures, as
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:44402:90"/> 
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 29. with the reſt.</p>
               <p>A Second mark by which we may know them to be the ſame, is in relation to the nature and effects of them, as is already expreſſed, namely, that perſons have been led by them to the higheſt degree of wickedneſs, waxen worſe and worſe till they have been as vile as hell it ſelf, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly denying the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with the like.</p>
               <p>2. they will appear to be the greateſt myſtery of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity, in that Satan makes uſe of them to do his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:44402:90"/> works, which is to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Saints, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with ſuch as have the greateſt ſtrength to reſiſt him, and ſuch as have eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped him in all his other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, he now makes uſe of them as things that are moſt ſtrong to deceive by, as we may remember how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly he did prevail with them about five or ſix years ſince in this nation, when it was hard to find one perſon, much leſs a whole Church, that was not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with them; at which time was the height of their reign in general, though in
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:44402:91"/> ſome places many particular perſons are enſlaved by them unto this day; ſome under one name, ſome under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; at which time before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned my ſelf did expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience thoſe expreſſed in <hi>p.</hi> 113, 114. which I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded I ſhould not have done, had they not been ſo general, and of ſuch a bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching deceiving nature; for I can truly ſay, ſo far as I did experience them, I was meerly deceived and begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from an apprehended worth and excellency in them; and as it was with me, ſo I believe it was with many
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:44402:91"/> others, whom the Lord hath recovered from them. But</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be of a ſtrange decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nature, and ſo the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt myſtery of iniquity, if we conſider, that many of the moſt eminent Saints in thoſe daies were moſt incident to be deceived by them, I mean the moſt eminent as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal grace and qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and as to a ſtrict con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, though I cannot ſay as to a ſound Judgement, in knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the principles of truth; for queſtionleſs there was ſomthing of that nature
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:44402:92"/> wanting; for had they been as well principled in truth, as they were really united to truth, they would have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned Satan at a diſtance, and not been ſo deceived by him; and that I conceive was the very reaſon why ſo many were deceived in thoſe daies: for having been a long time in darkneſs and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, being but newly brought from under the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyterian yokes, they were generally weak in Judgement, though (it may be) ſtrong in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo the more eaſily deceived; like children rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:44402:92"/> to catch up any thing that hath a glorious appearance, not weighing and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether it be really ſo.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon I conceive why ſuch precious ones were ſo ſubject to be deceived in thoſe daies, was from an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme in minding truth as it relates to the inward man in point of experience, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward workings; which is in it ſelf very good; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an extreme on that hand, Satan took advantage by it, and preſented things in a plauſible ſeeming ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual appearance, beguiled and deceived them before they
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:44402:93"/> were aware. We are ſubject to extremes on all hands; ſome do mind truth ſo much in an outward way as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to Order and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as Baptiſm, Church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and the like, that they mind little elſe as to the end of theſe; and ſome are in the extreme on the other hand, and ſo while they were eagerly purſuing after the myſtery of truth as to their intentions, they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled with the myſtery of iniquity: much like that of the Jews concerning the Law <hi>Rom. 9. 3. They ſought after righteouſneſs, but did not attain
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:44402:93"/> it, Wherefore? becauſe they ſought it not by faith:</hi> So theſe ſought after truth really as to their intentions, but did not attain it, wherefore? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſought it not in the way of God; They ſought it not in his way as it relates to the Ordinances and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt, in way of obedience and privilege to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but only as it relates to the inward man by way of privilege; and as the Jewes were ſtrict in legal righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, ſo theſe did not run into waies of ſin; neither (I believe) can many of them charge themſelves with any
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:44402:94"/> ſin as that which occaſioned it at firſt, but only weakneſs in Judgement, not being well principled, and ſo not having an equal eſteem of all truth.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon why ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Saints were ſo deceived in thoſe daies, as I apprehend, was, That they being but newly come to the faith were expoſ'd to great temptations, having but little means of ſtrength againſt them, it may be far from a Church, or elſe in a Church where were falſe Teachers, as in thoſe dayes there were very many, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which many were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:44402:94"/> whereas others, who were as weak, if not weaker, being in Churches where there were ſound Teachers, were kept from them: which may be a caution, as to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, to take heed what and whom they hear, ſo to Churches, who they permit to be Teachers, and not to ſuffer any unſound doctrine to be taught. It may alſo be a word of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to all that do enjoy this great mercy to have ſound and faithful Teachers, <hi>highly to esteem them for their works ſake, and to account ſuch worthy of double honour,</hi> giving
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:44402:95"/> them all due reſpect and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, that they may do their work with joy, and not with grief, according to <hi>Hebrews 13. 17. 1 Theſſal. 5. 12, 13. 1 Timothy</hi> 5. 17. Other reaſons may be given for the Saints miſtake in thoſe things, but I ſhall mention no more, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only my own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. For I can truly ſay, that upon a diligent ſearch and enquiry what might be the cauſe of my own mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, I find them to be no other but theſe very things expreſt. As</p>
               <p>Firſt I was weak in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:44402:95"/> as indeed I had never been under much means to be otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I am conſcious to my ſelf of ſome extreme in minding truth as it relates to the inward man, though truly I know not that I did ſlight any Ordinance or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, but that I did rather highly eſteem of them; but not to leſſen ſin, it is poſſible there may be ſomething of that nature, though I know it not.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I am ſure I was expoſed to great temptations of this kind, having little means of ſtrength againſt
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:44402:96"/> them, finding ſo many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, though through mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy it is better now, that breach being made up with great advantage, for which I deſire with all Saints to praiſe the Lord for ever; for doubtleſs the Saints advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in their enlarged expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and confirmation in the truth is ſo great by theſe things that I cannot expres it. Again, it calls for praiſe, that as the Lord hath turned it to our great advantage, ſo he hath wonderfully diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the expectations of the devil, and wicked men, who were ready to ſay as in
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:44402:96"/> 
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 35. 25. All ſo would we have it, verily concluding, that though they could not ſuppreſs us by their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting power, yet now we would deſtroy our ſelves, as indeed we might have ſo done, had not the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; and we may ſay it was the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</p>
               <p>And whereas ſome by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe things have been ready to queſtion our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, whether it be of God; Let them know, that there is no ground from thence to queſtion it, ſeeing it is no more than what hath been
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:44402:97"/> in thoſe Churches in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles daies, and what they did foretell ſhould be in theſe daies, 1 <hi>Corinth. 15. 12. 1 Timothy 1. 19. 2 Timothy 2. 18. 2 Peter 2. 12. Acts</hi> 20. 30. But if it were a ſafe ground to judge of truth by what hath appeared in relation to thoſe things, then there is more ground of confirmation that what we practiſe is of God, ſeeing that notwithſtanding thoſe things we have been ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully preſerved as we are unto this day; but though theſe things may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as to the ignorant, yet
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:44402:97"/> yet the rule by which we judge of our practice, is only as it hath its ground and riſe in holy Scripture, being built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner Stone: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath never been any ſcruple at all to me; for though ſome have denyed the Churches, and turned their ears from hearing the truth, and have turned to fables, yet the Churches and truth is the ſame, as God is the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now as for the grounds or reaſons why ſome of the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:44402:98"/> Saints themſelves have ſo done, I ſhall ſay nothing, becauſe, as I ſaid before, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend no more but my own experience, and through the mercy of God I was never ſo far corrupted as to queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion either the Scriptures, Churches, or Ordinances of Chriſt, much leſs to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from them, or to give any juſt occaſion to be withdrawn from by them; yet notwithſtanding I do not in the leaſt queſtion the reality of thoſe poor ſouls who have been ſo far over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and are through mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy again returned: and as
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:44402:98"/> for ſuch as never return, I ſhall leave them to be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord, who only is the judge of thoſe that are without, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 13. Having thus far conſidered of theſe allegorical notions, how they are the worſt of all errors, and the greateſt myſtery of iniquity, in that they are more deceiving than others, promiſing the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good, but leading di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the greateſt evil, and having given ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as I judge, why the Saints in theſe daies have been ſo generally deceived by them; I ſhall further
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:44402:99"/> proceed to conſider what may be the end of God in permitting it ſo to be.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I conceive it may be in general, that ſuch as were approved may be made manifeſt, agreeable to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 9. which accordingly hath been; many by thoſe things were made manifeſt to be approved, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were not, have appeared to be what they are. But</p>
               <p>Secondly, and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, I believe the Lord had many good ends in it, both in relation to himſelf, in relation to them, and in
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:44402:99"/> relation to others of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it may be ſome that are yet unborn.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In relation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for the exaltation of his praiſe, that when they ſhould come to ſee how great their deliverance was, and what an addition to all their former mercies, they might admire his goodneſs, and break forth into the high praiſes of his name, and that all the daies of their lives, when this mercy comes into their thoughts. For my own particular I can truly ſay, that the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God to me in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:44402:100"/> to thoſe things, I look upon it as the greateſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that ever I received from the Lord, next the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of his Love in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt through the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. But</p>
               <p>Secondly, In relation to them ſo deceived, that they ſhould have enlarged expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the fulneſs of God, and of their own nothing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of the ſweetneſs and excellency of truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove error, how it doth excell it as far as light excells darkneſs, and live more upon God, and leſs upon themſelves, in faith and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:44402:100"/> humility, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all grace, in more cleerneſs of underſtanding and knowledge of the Truth, for doubtleſs through the goodneſs of the Lord, who hath promiſed to do his people good by every thing, they do gain by it in all theſe in ſome meaſure; for my own particular, I muſt needs ſay, though I am ſtill but weak, yet through mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy my gain by thoſe things is ſo great, that I would not be without it, though I deſire not to purchaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more at that rate.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In relation to
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:44402:101"/> others, that through their experience, they might be the more able to forewarn others, who may meet with the like temptations; for certainly had the Saints in thoſe daies had that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Satans work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in that nature, which now they have, and had the Mouth of truth been ſo open againſt it as it is at this day, it would doubtleſs have prevented much; and therefore by the way I muſt needs ſay, I am perſwaded it will be a great aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſin, for any to be taken or held by thoſe
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:44402:101"/> things when there is ſo much means to avoid them, as through the mercy of God there is in theſe daies almoſt in every place. Now the Lord having theſe and other ſuch like ends in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thoſe things, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that my ſelf with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who have experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them in any meaſure, may be carefull to anſwer thoſe ends; for doubtleſs if our deliverance be of God, and that we are cleerly brought off from thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, we ſhall anſwer all thoſe ends of God in ſome meaſure.</p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:44402:102"/>
               <p>In the next place, as to the way and means by which the Lord hath been pleaſed to recover his people from theſe things, I ſhall ſay lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, becauſe I believe it hath been various, ſome by one means, ſome by another, as they were in various Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; for my own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar I have declared at large how it was with me, only theſe General heads I ſhall again remind.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I was brought into great ſtraits and much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in Judgement.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Lord was pleaſed to withdraw his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:44402:102"/> from me.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Being ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that confuſion, and want of communion with God, I was put upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into my own heart, what might be the reaſons of it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It pleaſed the Lord to make me willing to be informed, and to examine things by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, he was pleaſed to draw forth my heart with much earneſtneſs to ſeek to him by prayer, which through great mercy was largely anſwered.</p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:44402:103"/>
               <p>And thus I doubt not, but by what I have written it will appear that I have not, without good grounds both from Scripture and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Judged thoſe things to be the greated myſtery of iniquity, and the moſt dangerous, and worſt of all errors.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot but mind ſomething further, as to the continuation of thoſe things, which is, as they are the worſt of all others, ſo their time is ſhort; for according to my moſt ſerious obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherever they come,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:44402:103"/> and where they continue longeſt, their riſe, reign, and ruin, is all accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in a few years; for in a ſhort time gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally perſons have been ſo confounded that they have either come to ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deluded, and ſo have turned from them, or elſe they have run to abſolute Atheiſm, and ſo ended there.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now only anſwer one objection, as to my own experience, and ſo end this diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Some have ſaid that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not judge of theſe things
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:44402:104"/> by experience, becauſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared I never had but little experience of them, but only in three or four things, and thoſe I could never ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come up to neither, in Judgement, nor practiſe, neither could I leave theſe outward things, which all muſt leave before they can ſee the glory of the inward. And thoſe that have not put themſelves on ſuch things, but were led to them by the Father, have and do ſee that glory.</p>
               <p>This Objection hath ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious words, but weighed
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:44402:104"/> in the ballance of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, will be found ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than vanity, with the reſt of the like nature, which, I hope, is already made manifeſt, only I ſhall add a few words by way of Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for my Experience as to my ſelf in particular, I confeſs through the mercy of God it was far ſhort of that which many precious ones in thoſe daies fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yet I can truly ſay it was ſo much as did cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover to me the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and tendency of them all, to be ſo vile, that I
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:44402:105"/> I do not know any thing that ever I did ſince I knew God that I can own with more ſhame to my ſelf than thoſe things.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for my expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience as to others, I have ſeen and known that ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to ſatisfy me, that there is no ſuch glory in them but a meer deluſion; but I deſire to judge by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience no otherwiſe than as it hath relation to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures; for though I do very highly eſteem of Chriſtian experience as to the operations and effects of truth in the ſoul, as indeed
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:44402:105"/> it is the very life of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, yet as to rule I value one word of Scripture more than all experience, and I am ſure the Scriptures will not own them, which are the rule and touch-ſtone by which I deſire to try and judge all things; For that which the Scripture ſets up, they throw down, and that which the Scripture forbids, they ſet up; for inſtance, the Scripture exalts the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in all his Actions, Offices and Ordinances, they ſet up ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in oppoſition to this, calling it fleſhly, carnal, and outward things, and for
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:44402:106"/> the fathers leading perſons to them, which words car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry indeed a ſeeming ſhew of excellency, but its a meer deluſion, There is no ſuch thing; for the Father and Chriſt are one, and what was appointed by Chriſt was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Father, <hi>John</hi> 10. 3. &amp; 14. 24. and he doth not lead from his own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, but thoſe that continue in them he will love, and he will ſend his Spirit to them, which ſhall abide with them for ever, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 16. and the Father and Chriſt will come to them, and make their abode with
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:44402:106"/> them, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. I having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready written that which may more fully anſwer this objection, ſhall ſay no more, but deſire that all the Lords people may be delivered and kept from ſuch deceivings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:44402:107"/>
               <head>The ſixt Note of Experience in relation to Qualifications, the habits of Grace or fruits of the Spirit, how and by what means I have and do daily find an increaſe or decreaſe in thoſe things.</head>
               <p>TO make way for me to lay down my thoughts as to gracious qualifications, I ſhall firſt conſider the ſeverall kinds of qualifications, which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive may be three, 1. Moral, 2. Legal, 3. Goſpel.</p>
               <p>By Moral I mean ſuch as are from Moral dictates meerly from nature, Civility, breeding or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation.</p>
               <p>By Legal I mean ſuch as are from legal dictates, meerly from
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:44402:107"/> fear of wrath, without any cleer apprehenſions of the free grace of God in the Goſpel. But here I deſire to be very tender, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is poſſible there may be ſome ſeeds of the Goſpell ſowen in ſuch hearts, by which thoſe qualifications may be wrought, though as yet it may not appear, neither to themſelves nor others, that they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Goſpel; this only as to poſſibilities, for ordinarily it is not ſo.</p>
               <p>But thirdly, by Goſpel quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, I mean ſuch as are from Goſpel dictates, from a cleer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the free grace of God therein, being conſtrained from the Love of Chriſt, and in obedience to the commands and authority of Chriſt, the ſoul giving up it ſelf in all things to be like him, ſuch as are wrought
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:44402:108"/> by the Goſpel and ſpirit received they and they only are the fruits of the ſpirit; but as for thoſe other qualifications, perſons that are ignorant of the Goſſpel, and have not received the Spirit, may be eminent in them which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for that they have ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are great ornaments as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, though as to inward glory they do many times prove miſerable ornaments, being props and ſtaies that keep ſuch perſons from coming to Chriſt, and as it was ſaid of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 31. Publicans and Harlots do enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome rather than they; and this I have experienced, that as to my receiving Chriſt upon Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel terms, there was nothing ſo hard to me as to lay aſide all thoſe qualifications as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:44402:108"/> expreſt in my third and fourth notes of experiences.</p>
               <p>Now for the fruits of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit what they are, is expreſſed both in general and particular terms, in general <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 9. the fruits of the ſpirit is in all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, righteouſneſs and truth, more particularly <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22, 23. the fruit of the ſpirit is <hi>Love, Joy, Peace, Long ſuffering, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Temperance,</hi> &amp;c. alſo there are other things expreſſed in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther terms in Scriptures which doubtleſs are likewiſe fruits of the ſpirit, though I think with ſubmiſſion to better Judgements all others are included in theſe, whether it be ſelf denyal, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, humility, or the like, Theſe things are excellent orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which do adorn Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the eyes of men, and do
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:44402:109"/> redound much to the glory of God, and therefore very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable for Saints to preſs after them by all means.</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs that in the viewing of my own heart I have many times been much grieved to ſee how ſhort I come in all theſe things, but eſpecially in ſome of them, yet through grace I can ſay I have received a meaſure of them all, and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience do know, if my heart deceive me not, wherein I am weak, and wherein ſtrong, and though I am ſure in thoſe in which I am ſtrongeſt I am but weak, conſidering how I ought to be.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhall ſpeak a little how and by what means according to my experience, and as I judge ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture rule, theſe things do increaſe or decreaſe in Saints.</p>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:44402:109" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Firſt, I conceive they increaſe and are ſtrengthened by a cloſe walking with God in all ſpiritual duties, eſpecially private duties, meditation, ſelf-examination, ſelf-watching, ſelf-judging, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humbling and prayer, which are indeed ſuch duties, as no hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite can truly do, not that theſe private duties are above publick but that they prepare for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and by theſe we are acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with our own hearts, &amp; come to know wherein we are weak, and wherin ſtrong, what we have received, and what we want, and ſo how to apply our ſelves to <hi>God</hi> in publick and private, for the ſubduing of ſuch a corruption, or for the ſupply of ſuch or ſuch a grace, and this according to my experience, as I have walked more or leſs cloſe with God in theſe private duties, ſo is my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:44402:110"/> in publique duties, and my ſtrength in qualifications, the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of grace more or leſs, and I am confident, that ſuch perſons as are ſtrangers to theſe private duties, are alſo ſtrangers to their own hearts, and will not make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great progreſs in Chriſtianity; for in the omiſſion of theſe we are ſubject to be exerciſed in things contrary, which do very much interrupt our communion with God, and ſo weaken the power of every grace in us, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weaken the power of grace in all its effects: for theſe things are not properly graces, but the effects of grace, which are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſo improperly call'd gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as when we do not daily hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves before the Lord, we are ſubject to exalt our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, and when we do not watch our own hearts and judge
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:44402:110"/> our ſelves, we are ſubject to be judging others, and to watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them in an evil way, &amp; when we do not dayly meditate on thoſe excellent qualifications that were in Chriſt himſelf, we are ſubject to ſee little lovelineſs in them, and ſo having a light e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of them, not to preſs after them, whereas we are to imitate him in all theſe things, according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28, 29. But ſecondly, The habits of grace, or fruits of the ſpirit do increaſe or decreaſe as we do more or leſs exerciſe that meaſure of them already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and every particular grace is increaſed by the exerciſe of it ſelf, and ſo by much exerciſe (I mean by dayly acts) they do as it were become natural, as it is ſaid of <hi>Timotheus Phi.</hi> 2. 20. and the exerciſe of faith doth directly lead us to the fountain of grace,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:44402:111"/> in beholding of which glory of God we are changed into the ſame image, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18. there is ſuch a transforming nature in it, that the very beholding of it transforms us into the ſame like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2. and I can truly ſay from bleſſed experience, that in the exerciſe of that meaſure of grace I have received, thus lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to behold the Lord Jeſus in what he hath done for me, I have found it more advantagious for the deſtroying of corruption and for the ſtrengthening me in thoſe things, than in any other means whatſoever; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why many perſons do ſit a long time in the profeſſion of truth, and yet continue weak, ignorant, barren, and fruitleſs branches, it is becauſe as they are remiſs in private duties, ſo they do not exerciſe that meaſure of
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:44402:111"/> grace received, and ſo by a heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, careleſs, carnall walking, the heart grows carnal, and their is rather a decreaſe than increaſe in all ſpiritual ſtrength.</p>
               <p>But ſome will ſay, can any do theſe things of themſelves? and doth not God give grace freely both in and after converſion?</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, yea, but in the work of converſion we are paſſive, I mean as to inward ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual activity, we can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being dead, according to <hi>Epheſ. 2. 1. 2 Cor. 5. 14. Joh.</hi> 5. 25. not excluding thoſe duties which God requires from all, as hearing the Goſpel, reading, &amp;c. through which God hath promiſed to convey ſpiritual life, <hi>Eſay 55. 3. Rom.</hi> 10. 17. but after converſion we are active, and therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to keep our ſelves in the love of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Jude 12. To add to our
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:44402:112"/> faith, vertue, to vertue knowledge,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Pet. 1. 5. with many other ſuch like Scriptures, <hi>Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to do any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 5. who is pleaſed to give in dayly ſupplies, and in the dayly exerciſe of what we have to give us more, yet all of grace, freely, and ſo grace for grace, as appears in the 1. of <hi>John</hi> 6. yet notwithſtanding all that I have written, I judge that its poſſible ſome Saints may be very diligent in the uſe of all means, for the ſubduing of ſome particular corruptions, and for the ſupply of ſome particular grace, and yet not attain it, but God is pleaſed to withhold it from them, and leſt they ſhould be to much exalted, to leave ſome corruption for them to
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:44402:112"/> ſtrive, and ſtruggle with, it may be as long as they live, which for ought I know was <hi>Pauls</hi> very caſe 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 8. and the Lord may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe one grace in us by the want of another, yea all by the want of one, not that Saints are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all in their nature, but as to a greater meaſure in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; and ſo far as I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, this though I am ſtill ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſuſpect my own diligence in the uſe of means, I can truly ſay, That God is never wanting in ſuch caſes, with ſupports from himſelf, ſaying, my grace is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for thee, my power is made manifeſt in weakneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9. and though ſin be in you, it ſhall ſhall not reign there, neither ſhall it have dominion over you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>yea are not under the law, but under Grace,</hi> Rom. 6. 11, 12, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. I ſhall ſay no more now of theſe
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:44402:113"/> things, but beg of God that my ſelf with all Saints may preſs more after them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:44402:113"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>HAving thus far writtenof my <hi>Experience</hi> in ſeveral general heads, which do include many particular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, I had ſome thoughts to have written of many other things, but my Book being almoſt full, I ſhall conclude with a few lines as to Experience it ſelf, what it is, how, and by what means it is attained.</p>
               <p>There be various things about which perſons may be exerciſed in way of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet all may be divided
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:44402:114"/> under one of theſe two heads, its either in relation to the world, or in relation to God; as to that of the World, its all but <hi>vanity and vexation of ſpirit,</hi> Eccl. 1. 14. <hi>and he that uncreaſeth knowledge</hi> in thoſe things, <hi>increaſeth ſorrow,</hi> verſe 18. and though there may be ſomething of that nature convenient for Saints to know upon a natural or civil account, its but periſhing at beſt, and therefore too low for them to ſpend much of their precious time and thoughts about: Its their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege to have inlarged ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in the great things
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:44402:114"/> of God, things that are laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and durable to eternity; and as godly perſons may have experience in ſome things of the world, ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal perſons may have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the dealings of God in ſome things, as to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny outward bleſſings and deliverances by a common hand of providence, in which they do many times ſo bleſs themſelves, as if they were highly in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with God, when the Lord knows it is no ſuch thing, but it may be they have their portion in this life, and are delivered
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:44402:115"/> from a leſſer, to be reſerved to a greater deſtruction.</p>
               <p>But as to Experience from a trueſanctified knowledge, or ſpecial work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrangers to it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. its only the privilege of Saints to be eminent in that; and indeed its a privilege ſo great, that I deſire for ever to bleſs the Lord that he hath made me, who am ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, in any meaſure to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of it; for things meerly hiſtorical or traditional will vaniſh and come to nothing, and ſo far as we partake of truth, not onely in its princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:44402:115"/> as to the underſtanding of it from Scripture rule, but alſo in its experience as to the effects and operations of it in our hearts, ſo far it will ſtand us inſtead, and ſo far do we attain true wiſdome, and no farther; and indeed as to the effects and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it in the heart, it is the very life of Chriſtianity; yet as to rule for the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of any principle one word of Scripture is more worth than all our experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and as to the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of evil its better to learn that any way, than by the experience of it, for ſo its the ſchool of fools; yet wiſe
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:44402:116"/> men have ſo learned in ſome things; now according to my underſtanding, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more than a bare knowledge, it is either a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getter, or an effect of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and hath alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to ſome rule, whether it be in natural or ſpiritual things; if in natural things, it muſt anſwer a rule of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if in ſpiritual, it muſt anſwer a ſpiritual rule, and the holy Scripture is that rule, by which all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an experience muſt be tried, according to the Lords own appointment, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8. 20. and all muſt anſwer ſome rule
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:44402:116"/> therein expreſt or implyed; by rule in this ſenſe I mean the Scriptures, declaring the ſame thing; and as it muſt anſwer a rule in it ſelf, ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that knowledge and underſtanding which perſons have in the rule, ſo is the meaſure of their experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: For though ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have much knowledge as to principles, and but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle experience, yet none can have experience of that they do not underſtand, either in a principle before they had that experience, or elſe they have learned that principle by experience; for (as I ſaid
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:44402:117"/> before) all experience is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an effect of knowledge, or by it we learn knowledge, otherwiſe it cannot be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; this I mind the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe ſome perſons do pleaſe themſelves with a conceited experience, though ignorant in the principles of truth, when there cannot be ſuch a thing. I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I have been grieved to hear ſuch perſons ſpeak of their experience, when it doth appear to me, as it is ſaid of ſome that would be Preachers of the Law, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 7. they know not what they ſay, nor whereof they
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:44402:117"/> affirm, and theſe are two ſorts of perſons, firſt, ſuch as through ignorance of the Scriptures do imagine that to be Chriſtian experience, which doth not anſwer a rule of Scripture, but is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereto. 2. Such as from corrupt principles will ſet up their experience above or equal to the authority of Scripture, as to give a being to inſtitutions, or to make it a rule to judge and try all things, yea the very Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf, when both it and they muſt be judged therby <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 16. There is much corrupt experience in the world, and perſons have been
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:44402:118"/> as much miſtaken in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, eſpecially in theſe daies, as in any thing I know, and no marvel, when they leave the Scriptures as to rule &amp; walk by the uncertain rule of their own <hi>experience,</hi> which many times is nothing but the <hi>viſion</hi> of their own brains; yet notwithſtanding the great miſtakes of many through corrupt experience, yet true Chriſtian experience is as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent as ever, and that as I ſaid before is more than a bare knowledge, it is truth brought home to the heart with life and power, by the Spirit of God conforming the ſoul in all things to the will
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:44402:118"/> of God, being united to Chriſt by faith, and ſo by it we learn many things; Firſt, by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience we find the word of God daily accompliſhed in us, and are confirmed in our faith and hope, for <hi>experience worketh hope, Rom.</hi> 5. 4. by it we come to be acquainted with our own hearts, and are not ſo eaſily deceived by them; by experience we learn how to uſe our ſpiritual armor, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 12, 13, 14. for offence and defence againſt the wiles of the devil, not being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his deviſes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 11. by it we learn wiſdom as to the exerciſe of all ſpiritual
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:44402:119"/> gifts, and do know what we have received, and what we want in a meaſure, and what will help or hinder a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous frame in us; alſo by it we learn wiſdom as to the profiting by all conditions, and as to the anſwering of all relations, and in all theſe perſons do many times do that for want of experience, which after they have more, they are aſhamed of what they have done; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that meaſure of it which through grace I have attain'd, I have often thought that a large experienced Chriſtian doth as far excell
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:44402:119"/> and differ from ſuch as have but little experience, as a man differs from a child, and may ſay as <hi>Iob</hi> did, <hi>I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear, but now mine eyes ſee thee,</hi> Job 42. 5. and becauſe experience is a thing ſo excellent, every one would be eminent in it, or at leaſt they would be thought to be ſo, when the truth is there are but few that do take a right courſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it. Now for the way and means by which it is attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I ſhall give my thoughts, 1. I conceive its the fruit of much Chriſtian labour after long continuance in the truth and being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="206" facs="tcp:44402:120"/> various conditions. But 2. and chiefly I apprehend it is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by ſerious obſervation and meditation: for though perſons may have much knowledge as to the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of truth, and may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long in the profeſſion of it, and may be exerciſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der many changes, yet if they are not ſerious in their obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, but things come and go with them, and they not regard it, they will never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to much experience; whereas it may be ſome that are more ſerious and obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that have not bin ſo long in the truth, or ſo exerciſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="207" facs="tcp:44402:120"/> than they, as ſome children will learn more in a moneth than others in a year, but this is not ordinary; for though perſons may be long in the truth, and have but little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, yet ſuch as are new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to the faith cannot have much, though never ſo obſerving; for which cauſe young Chriſtians are not to be choſen Church-officers, being ſubject to be ſoon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by temptations; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo let young Chriſtians eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, <hi>Be ſwift to hear, and ſlow to ſpeak,</hi> Iam. 1. 19. and be more <hi>ſwift to hear than to offer the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of fools,</hi> Eccle. 5. 1. Seeing it is ſo that <hi>Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:44402:121"/> in its place is a thing ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and that the means by which its attained is by ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſervation, I deſire with all Saints to give up my ſelf to a ſerious obſervation of the dealings of <hi>God</hi> with us in all conditions, that we may not receive mercies in vain, but that we may treaſure them up in our <hi>Christian experience,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in our <hi>treaſury things new and old,</hi> that we may be ready upon all occaſions to bring it forth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 52. to the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>praiſe</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> &amp; to the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> &amp; <hi>comfort</hi> of our <hi>ſelves</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> as its <hi>our duty</hi> ſo to do, till the <hi>comming</hi> of <hi>our Lord,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>glory</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:44402:121"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
